<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-20T11:27:32-05:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Data &amp;amp; AI Blog</title><subtitle>From Data To Actionable Insights</subtitle><entry><title type="html">5 Tips for DS/AI Beginners &amp;amp; Enthusiasts</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/26/5-tips-for-ds-ai-beginners-enthusiasts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 Tips for DS/AI Beginners &amp; Enthusiasts" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/26/5-tips-for-ds-ai-beginners-enthusiasts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/26/5-tips-for-ds-ai-beginners-enthusiasts.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*WYAntO3ZfXBMkyn31mHoRw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Sam Truong Dan](https://unsplash.com/@sam_truong?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/search/photos/tips?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post, I am sharing 5 important tips for budding data scientists, there is a bonus tip as well in the end.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I believe that the more you struggle, the more you get to learn in the process, you can still learn from experienced professionals to avoid common roadblocks or challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS/AI starters and enthusiasts keep interacting with me and I try to help them. Apart from common questions by them, I give them tips on how they can become effective in their DS/AI journey, i.e. what to focus and what to avoid etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am sharing 5 of those tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;master-thebasics&quot;&gt;Master The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*KSja_FQfoEm-sRMao1VD6g.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can work on any DS/AI problem, you need to master the basics. Understand the mathematics required for DS/AI, which is Linear Algebra, Multivariate Calculus, Statistics &amp;amp; Probability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then learn about frequently used algorithms like Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, Decision Trees, Random Forest etc. Where to apply which algorithm and what are the advantages and limitations of using a particular algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand the overall process of working in DS/AI projects, from defining the problem to deploying the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improve your coding skills to execute &amp;amp; validate your hypothesis efficiently. Python &amp;amp; R are the two major languages preferred by data scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learn-justenough&quot;&gt;Learn Just Enough&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*WzniU-FFsxpxKx5aglBU1g.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS/AI is a vast field, one can not be an expert overnight. The biggest mistake newbies do is to get stuck into an endless learning loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are learning DS/AI is to solve real-world problems, so learn just enough concepts to get started. Participate in hackathons/competitions, practice on public datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need not read each book or attend every course on the planet before feeling confident to start with DS/AI. Just follow one decent book or course to build your basics and start working on problems. Keep the material (books &amp;amp; courses) for reference in case you get stuck with your problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;handle-data-like-apro&quot;&gt;Handle Data Like a Pro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*YAYqqk7M7wQ28U7sVh1oQA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is the heart of DS/AI initiatives &amp;amp; projects. If you can’t handle data, you can’t make progress with your use case. Data handling can make or break any DS/AI project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build your skills in data handling, learn frequently used tips &amp;amp; tricks in SQL, Pandas (in Python) or data.table (in R) to handle &amp;amp; manipulate data efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn from Kaggle kernels, popular GitHub repos, how experts handle the data. Gather and clean public datasets on your own and refer these resources wherever get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-thecontext&quot;&gt;Understand The Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*ChpN6CWwu61TEP-V.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a newbie data scientist, you may be tempted to get the highest accuracy you can on any DS/AI problem you are working. But the real world is quite different, it’s not about the accuracy every time, many times robustness is very important and most of the time, the business may need models to be more interpretable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every framework, every feature has its own use case. If a particular approach worked in your previous project, the same may not work in the current one. As we say, there is no silver bullet in DS/AI field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence understanding the context of the problem or the use case is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improve-communication&quot;&gt;Improve Communication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*9ZDJW08N1FZlPIFu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the problem or use case, to get the overall context from business, to explain outcomes of your complex models requires excellent communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting your approaches and findings to a non-technical audience, such as the marketing team or the CXOs, is a crucial part of being a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to have the ability to interpret data, tell the stories contained therein, and in general, communicate, write and present well. Presentation, Storytelling, Data Visualization, Writing/Publishing, Business Insights, all are part of communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have to work hard to develop these skills — the same as you would with any technical skills. But with time and practice, you can get really good at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-tip-develop-t-shaped-skill-set&quot;&gt;Bonus Tip: Develop T-shaped Skill-set&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*5VE1BaIQGTmXCxIx.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS/AI is an interdisciplinary field, and you can get expertise in one area at a time. Still, I would suggest you develop T-shaped skill-set to collaborate better with experts in other related fields working with you in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T-shaped skills describe specific attributes of desirable workers. The vertical bar of the T refers to expert knowledge and experience in a particular area, while the top of the T refers to an ability to collaborate with experts in other disciplines and a willingness to use the knowledge gained from this collaboration. A t-shaped person is someone with t-shaped skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCrIv4EU2tFX8VhhT0oCnDnw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this post, I am sharing 5 important tips for budding data scientists, there is a bonus tip as well in the end. While I believe that the more you struggle, the more you get to learn in the process, you can still learn from experienced professionals to avoid common roadblocks or challenges. DS/AI starters and enthusiasts keep interacting with me and I try to help them. Apart from common questions by them, I give them tips on how they can become effective in their DS/AI journey, i.e. what to focus and what to avoid etc. Here I am sharing 5 of those tips: Master The Basics Before you can work on any DS/AI problem, you need to master the basics. Understand the mathematics required for DS/AI, which is Linear Algebra, Multivariate Calculus, Statistics &amp;amp; Probability. Then learn about frequently used algorithms like Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, Decision Trees, Random Forest etc. Where to apply which algorithm and what are the advantages and limitations of using a particular algorithm. Understand the overall process of working in DS/AI projects, from defining the problem to deploying the solution. Improve your coding skills to execute &amp;amp; validate your hypothesis efficiently. Python &amp;amp; R are the two major languages preferred by data scientists. Learn Just Enough DS/AI is a vast field, one can not be an expert overnight. The biggest mistake newbies do is to get stuck into an endless learning loop. You are learning DS/AI is to solve real-world problems, so learn just enough concepts to get started. Participate in hackathons/competitions, practice on public datasets. You need not read each book or attend every course on the planet before feeling confident to start with DS/AI. Just follow one decent book or course to build your basics and start working on problems. Keep the material (books &amp;amp; courses) for reference in case you get stuck with your problem. Handle Data Like a Pro Data is the heart of DS/AI initiatives &amp;amp; projects. If you can’t handle data, you can’t make progress with your use case. Data handling can make or break any DS/AI project. Build your skills in data handling, learn frequently used tips &amp;amp; tricks in SQL, Pandas (in Python) or data.table (in R) to handle &amp;amp; manipulate data efficiently. Learn from Kaggle kernels, popular GitHub repos, how experts handle the data. Gather and clean public datasets on your own and refer these resources wherever get stuck. Understand The Context As a newbie data scientist, you may be tempted to get the highest accuracy you can on any DS/AI problem you are working. But the real world is quite different, it’s not about the accuracy every time, many times robustness is very important and most of the time, the business may need models to be more interpretable. Every framework, every feature has its own use case. If a particular approach worked in your previous project, the same may not work in the current one. As we say, there is no silver bullet in DS/AI field. Hence understanding the context of the problem or the use case is important. Improve Communication To understand the problem or use case, to get the overall context from business, to explain outcomes of your complex models requires excellent communication skills. Presenting your approaches and findings to a non-technical audience, such as the marketing team or the CXOs, is a crucial part of being a data scientist. You need to have the ability to interpret data, tell the stories contained therein, and in general, communicate, write and present well. Presentation, Storytelling, Data Visualization, Writing/Publishing, Business Insights, all are part of communication skills. You may have to work hard to develop these skills — the same as you would with any technical skills. But with time and practice, you can get really good at it. Bonus Tip: Develop T-shaped Skill-set DS/AI is an interdisciplinary field, and you can get expertise in one area at a time. Still, I would suggest you develop T-shaped skill-set to collaborate better with experts in other related fields working with you in the project. T-shaped skills describe specific attributes of desirable workers. The vertical bar of the T refers to expert knowledge and experience in a particular area, while the top of the T refers to an ability to collaborate with experts in other disciplines and a willingness to use the knowledge gained from this collaboration. A t-shaped person is someone with t-shaped skills. Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on YouTube, Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Useful Resources to Learn Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/01/useful-resources-to-learn-artificial-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Useful Resources to Learn Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2020-03-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/01/useful-resources-to-learn-artificial-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/03/01/useful-resources-to-learn-artificial-intelligence.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*6AyOAQu0Q9ivgvfeY9MIRQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Markus Spiske](https://unsplash.com/photos/Q0mDOn9gWk8?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/search/photos/resources?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you are learning Artificial Intelligence (AI) and looking to get into this exciting field, you may wonder which are the resources to refer, how do you know if a book or course is worth to spend time and/or money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Due to close association between Data Science (DS), Machine Learning (ML) and Artificial Intelligence (AI), these terms have been used in this article interchangeably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list by any means, but it is good enough to keep as your reference. You can build your own list of references once you get more awareness of the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is my attempt to make your task easier. I am listing down major quality resources (mostly free) here and also going to provide you with my view of these resources, which will help you to make an informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Ph24kcZtHvK51Pci0WFHSw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You need not go through each and every resource mentioned here, I would suggest you build the foundation first using a course or a book and keep other resources for your reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;books-torefer&quot;&gt;Books to refer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*KsUJovlo19BEon_wIynWNg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning-withr&quot;&gt;Machine Learning with R&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an excellent book for the R starter who wants to apply ML to any kind of project. All the main ML models are presented, as well as different performance metrics, bagging, pruning, tuning, ensembling etc. Easy to scan through, many tips with fully-solved textbook problems. Certainly, a very good starting point if you plan to compete on Kaggle. If you already master both R and ML, this books is obviously not for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-R-Brett-Lantz-ebook/dp/B00G9581JM&quot;&gt;Machine Learning with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;python-machinelearning&quot;&gt;Python Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic introductory book in machine learning with python. It provides enough background about the theory of each (covered) technique followed by its python code. One nice thing about the book is that it starts implementing Neural Networks from scratch, providing the reader with the chance of truly understanding the key underlying techniques such as back-propagation. Even further, the book presents an efficient (and professional) way of coding in python, the key to AI/ML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Python-Machine-Learning-scikit-learn-TensorFlow/dp/1789955750&quot;&gt;Python Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;islr&quot;&gt;ISLR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book explains the concepts of Statistical Learning from the very beginning. The core ideas such as bias-variance trade-off are deeply discussed and revisited in many problems. The included R examples are particularly helpful for beginners to learn R. The book also provides a brief, but concise description of functions’ parameters for many related R packages. Compared to &lt;em&gt;The Elements of Statistical Learning&lt;/em&gt;, it is easy for the reader to understand. It does a wonderful job of breaking things down complex concepts. If one wishes to learn more about a particular topic, I’d recommend The Element of Statistical Learning. These two pair nicely together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Statistical-Learning-Applications-Statistics/dp/1461471370&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Statistical Learning: with Applications in R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-learning&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the book to read on deep learning. Written by luminaries in the field — if you’ve read any papers on deep learning, you must have heard about Goodfellow and Bengio before — and cutting through much of the BS surrounding the topic: like ‘big data’ before it, ‘deep learning’ is not something new and is not deserving of a special name. Networks with more hidden layers to detect higher-order features, networks of different types chained together in order to play to their strengths, graphs of networks to represent a probabilistic model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a theoretical book, but it can be read in tandem with &lt;em&gt;Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn and TensorFlow&lt;/em&gt;, almost chapter-for-chapter. The Scikit-Learn and Tensorflow example code, while only moderately interesting on its own, helps to clarify the purpose of many of the topics in the Goodfellow book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deeplearningbook.org/&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hands-on-machine-learning-with-scikit-learn-and-tensorflow&quot;&gt;Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn and TensorFlow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book provides a great introduction to machine learning for both developer and non-developers. Authors suggest to just go through even if you don’t understand math details. Highlights of this book are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extraction of field expert knowledge is very important, you should know which model will serve better for the given solution. Luckily, a lot of models are available already from other scientists.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Training data is the most important part, the more you have it the better. So if you can you should accumulate as much data as you can, preferably categorized, you may not still know how you will apply the accumulated data in the future but you will need it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Labelling training data is very important too, to train neural network you need to have at least thousands of labelled data samples, the more the better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine learning algorithms and neural networks are pretty common for years but the latest breakthrough is possible because of new optimization, new autoencoders ( that may help to artificially generate training data) allowing to do training faster and with fewer data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine learning is still pretty time and resources consuming process. To train a machine learning model you need to know how to tweak parameters and how to use different training approaches fitting the particular model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book demonstrates (including the code) different approaches using Scikit-Learn python package and also the TensorFlow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Hands-Machine-Learning-Scikit-Learn-TensorFlow/dp/1492032646&quot;&gt;Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-science-forbusiness&quot;&gt;Data Science for Business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most practical book to read if you are looking for an overview of data science. Either you know when terms like k-means and ROC curves are to be used or you have some context when you start digging deeper into how some of these algorithms are implemented. You will find it at the right level because there is just enough math to explain the fundamental concepts and make them stick in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a book on implementing these concepts or a bunch of algorithms. This gives the book the advantage of being something you can refer to an intelligent manager or interested developer, and they can both get a lot out of it. And if they are interested in the next level of learning there are plenty of pointers. You will also find the chapter on presenting results through ROC curves, lift curves, etc. pretty interesting. It would be cool if this book had some more hands-on, but you can go to Kaggle and browse around the current and past competitions to apply what you learn here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Data-Science-Business-Data-Analytic-Thinking-ebook/dp/B00E6EQ3X4&quot;&gt;Data Science for Business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;courses-toattend&quot;&gt;Courses to attend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Fnr5qOz0l3Iv94uDmiKAgg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*kXMhOBDVRMz1Yw23eW5oSQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is one of the first programming MOOCs. Coursera put online by Coursera founder and Stanford Professor Andrew Ng. This course assumes that you have basic programming skills and you have some understanding of Linear Algebra. Knowledge of Statistics &amp;amp; Probability is not required though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Ng does a good job explaining dense material and slides. The course gives you a lot of structure and direction for each homework, so it is generally pretty clear what you are supposed to do and how you are supposed to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine Learning by Andrew Ng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-learning-1&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*B-YNpNbYhL7H3aV3FGJJhQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are rather new to the topic, you can learn a lot of doing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deeplearning.ai/&quot;&gt;deeplearning.ai&lt;/a&gt; specialization. First and foremost, you learn the basic concepts of NN. How does a forward pass in simple sequential models look like, what’s a backpropagation, and so on? I experienced this set of courses as a very time-effective way to learn the basics and worth more than all the tutorials, blog posts and talks, which I went through beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this specialization is probably more than the first step into DL. I would say, each course is a single step in the right direction, so you end up with five steps in total. I think it builds a fundamental understanding of the field. But going further, you have to practice a lot and eventually it might be useful also to read more about the methodological background of DL variants. But doing the course work gets you started in a structured manner — which is worth a lot, especially in a field with so much buzz around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/deep-learning&quot;&gt;Deep Learning Specialization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fast-ai&quot;&gt;Fast AI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*_zl5CsOf1wKVc5rf3nJtAQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your goal is to be able to learn about deep learning and apply what you’ve learned, the fast.ai course is a better bet. If you have the time, interleaving the deeplearning.ai and fast.ai courses is ideal — you get the practical experience, applicability, and audience interaction of fast.ai, along with the organised material and theoretical explanations of deeplearning.ai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://course.fast.ai/&quot;&gt;Fast AI Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kaggle-learn&quot;&gt;Kaggle Learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*adt-vqwPcEbKqno-X-j54w.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practical data skills you can apply immediately: that’s what you’ll learn in these free micro-courses. They’re the fastest (and most fun) way to become a data scientist or improve your current skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/learn/overview&quot;&gt;Kaggle Learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blogs-tofollow&quot;&gt;Blogs to follow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DPri3vSeJHubAvNX6qAdwQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kd-nuggets&quot;&gt;KD Nuggets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*PMf_rqIMEq7XmWMVo1DHaA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KDnuggets is a leading site on AI, Analytics, Big Data, Data Mining, Data Science, and Machine Learning and is edited by Gregory Piatetsky-Shapiro and Matthew Mayo. KDnuggets was founded in February of 1997. Before that, Gregory maintained an earlier version of this site, called Knowledge Discovery Mine, at GTE Labs (1994 to 1997).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kdnuggets.com&quot;&gt;KD Nuggets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analytics-vidhya&quot;&gt;Analytics Vidhya&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*xdh0J0cjzco-Fm7-6dEVtA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analytics Vidhya provides a community-based knowledge portal for Analytics and AI professionals. The aim of the platform is to become a complete portal serving all knowledge and career needs of Data Science Professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/&quot;&gt;Analytics Vidhya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;towards-datascience&quot;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*D9bFnt-SR_jwTCgdSLR3uA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TDS joined Medium’s vibrant community in October 2016. In the beginning, their goal was simply to gather good posts and distribute them to a broader audience. Just a few months later, they were pleased to see that they had a very fast-growing audience and many new contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today they are working with more than 10 Editorial Associates to prepare the most exciting content for our audience. They provide customized feedback to our contributors using Medium’s private notes. This allows them to promote their latest articles across social media without the added complexity that they might encounter using another platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com&quot;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;podcasts-tolisten&quot;&gt;Podcasts to listen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*my3rt5rEZQkm_OBmMbvfDg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-hack&quot;&gt;Data Hack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OTjq5-3vC8gk2pQ9W1Ummw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Analytics Vidhya’s exclusive podcast series which will feature top leaders and practitioners in the artificial intelligence and machine learning industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in every episode of DataHack Radio, they bring you discussions with one such thought leader in the industry. They have discussions about their journey, their learnings and plenty of other AI-related things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/category/podcast/&quot;&gt;Data Hack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;super-datascience&quot;&gt;Super Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*11x3RqCGDCkDGENLCx5Haw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kirill Eremenko&lt;/em&gt; is a Data Science coach and lifestyle entrepreneur. The goal of the &lt;em&gt;Super Data Science&lt;/em&gt; podcast is to bring you the most inspiring Data Scientists and Analysts from around the World to help you build your successful career in Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is growing exponentially and so are salaries of those who work in analytics. This podcast can help you learn how to skyrocket your analytics career. Big Data, visualization, predictive modelling, forecasting, analysis, business processes, statistics, R, Python, SQL programming, tableau, machine learning, Hadoop, databases, data science MBAs, and all the analytics tools and skills that will help you better understand how to crush it in Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.superdatascience.com/podcast&quot;&gt;Super Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-oreilly-data-showpodcast&quot;&gt;The O’Reilly Data Show Podcast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*GsfH3akVSuWLt9qO70zEOQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as the father of all other data shows, “the O’Reilly Data Show” features Ben Lorica, O’Reilly Media’s chief data scientist. Lorica conducts interviews with other experts about big data and data science current affairs. While it does get technical and may not be the best place for a beginner to start, it provides interesting insights into the future of the AI/ML industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/radar/topics/oreilly-data-show-podcast/&quot;&gt;Data Show&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youtube-channels&quot;&gt;YouTube Channels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*-mzvQ--w0193VMdl2p_6lg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deeplearningtv&quot;&gt;DeepLearning.TV&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*1GzebE9h8WVANeeInTXLYQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeepLearning.TV is all about Deep Learning, the field of study that teaches machines to perceive the world. Starting with a series that simplifies Deep Learning, the channel features topics such as How To’s, reviews of software libraries and applications, and interviews with key individuals in the field. Through a series of concept videos showcasing the intuition behind every Deep Learning method, they show you that Deep Learning is actually simpler than you think. Their goal is to improve your understanding of the topic so that you can better utilize Deep Learning in your own projects. They provide a window into the cutting edge of Deep Learning and bring you up to speed on what’s currently happening in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9OeZkIwhzfv-_Cb7fCikLQ&quot;&gt;DeepLearning.TV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-school&quot;&gt;Data School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ZLzNOlp1xjnha90gVqG5Ng.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you trying to learn data science so that you can get your first data science job? You’re probably confused about what you’re “supposed” to learn, and then you have the hardest time actually finding lessons you can understand! Data School focuses you on the topics you need to master first, and offers in-depth tutorials that you can understand regardless of your educational background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your host here is Kevin Markham, and he is the founder of Data School. He has taught data science using the Python programming language to hundreds of students in the classroom, and hundreds of thousands of students (like you) online. Finding the right teacher was so important to his data science education, and so he sincerely hopes that he can be the right data science teacher for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/dataschool&quot;&gt;Data School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caltech-machinelearning&quot;&gt;Caltech Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*o0eLbvhc-GFtU8nfbaolGQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory course by Caltech Professor &lt;em&gt;Yaser Abu-Mostafa&lt;/em&gt; on machine learning that covers the basic theory, algorithms, and applications. Machine learning (ML) enables computational systems to adaptively improve their performance with experience accumulated from the observed data. ML techniques are widely applied in engineering, science, finance, and commerce to build systems for which we do not have a full mathematical specification (and that covers a lot of systems). The course balances theory and practice and covers the mathematical as well as the heuristic aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLD63A284B7615313A\&quot;&gt;Caltech Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-repos&quot;&gt;GitHub Repos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*jiAe0f6Cv7psXiFOmtr8DQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awesome-datascience&quot;&gt;Awesome Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*cbw3xVbl67tXq9rCdrDhkQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Repo answer the questions, “What is Data Science and what should you study to learn Data Science?” An awesome Data Science repository to learn and apply for real-world problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the aggregator says, “Our favourite data scientist is Clare Corthell. She is an expert in data-related systems and a hacker and has been working on a company as a data scientist. Clare’s blog. This website helps you to understand the exact way to study as a professional data scientist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Secondly, Our favourite programming language is &lt;em&gt;Python&lt;/em&gt; nowadays for Data Science. Python’s — Pandas library has full functionality for collecting and analyzing data. We use Anaconda to play with data and to create applications.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/academic/awesome-datascience&quot;&gt;Awesome Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;essential-cheat-sheets-for-machine-learning-and-deep-learning-engineers&quot;&gt;Essential Cheat Sheets for Machine Learning and Deep Learning Engineers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*rJfSC9RVIKJS4GzizmMp2Q.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is complex. For newbies, starting to learn machine learning can be painful if they don’t have the right resources to learn from. Most of the machine learning libraries are difficult to understand and the learning curve can be a bit frustrating. Kailash Ahirwar has created a repository on Github (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kailashahirwar/cheatsheets-ai&quot;&gt;cheatsheets-ai&lt;/a&gt;) containing cheatsheets for different machine learning frameworks, gathered from different sources. Have a look at the Github repository, also, contribute cheat sheets if you have any. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kailashahirwar/cheatsheets-ai&quot;&gt;Essential Cheat Sheets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hackermath-for-machinelearning&quot;&gt;HackerMath for Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*qOEVgyamB11p5sYwfhBcKg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math literacy, including proficiency in Linear Algebra and Statistics, is a must for anyone pursuing a career in data science. The goal of this workshop is to introduce some key concepts from these domains that get used repeatedly in data science/AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As outlined by Amit Kapoor, “Our approach is what we call the ‘Hacker’s way’. Instead of going back to formulae and proofs, we teach the concepts by writing code. And in practical applications. Concepts don’t remain sticky if the usage is never taught.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus here is on depth rather than breadth. Three areas are chosen — Hypothesis Testing, Supervised Learning and Unsupervised Learning. They are covered to sufficient depth — 50% of the time on the concepts and 50% of the time spent coding them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amitkaps/hackermath&quot;&gt;HackerMath for Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is all that I needed to cover in this article. Now you know what useful resources you need to keep handy in order to get proficient in the field of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCrIv4EU2tFX8VhhT0oCnDnw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">While you are learning Artificial Intelligence (AI) and looking to get into this exciting field, you may wonder which are the resources to refer, how do you know if a book or course is worth to spend time and/or money? Due to close association between Data Science (DS), Machine Learning (ML) and Artificial Intelligence (AI), these terms have been used in this article interchangeably. This is not an exhaustive list by any means, but it is good enough to keep as your reference. You can build your own list of references once you get more awareness of the field. This post is my attempt to make your task easier. I am listing down major quality resources (mostly free) here and also going to provide you with my view of these resources, which will help you to make an informed decision. You need not go through each and every resource mentioned here, I would suggest you build the foundation first using a course or a book and keep other resources for your reference. Books to refer Machine Learning with R This is an excellent book for the R starter who wants to apply ML to any kind of project. All the main ML models are presented, as well as different performance metrics, bagging, pruning, tuning, ensembling etc. Easy to scan through, many tips with fully-solved textbook problems. Certainly, a very good starting point if you plan to compete on Kaggle. If you already master both R and ML, this books is obviously not for you. Machine Learning with R Python Machine Learning This is a fantastic introductory book in machine learning with python. It provides enough background about the theory of each (covered) technique followed by its python code. One nice thing about the book is that it starts implementing Neural Networks from scratch, providing the reader with the chance of truly understanding the key underlying techniques such as back-propagation. Even further, the book presents an efficient (and professional) way of coding in python, the key to AI/ML. Python Machine Learning ISLR The book explains the concepts of Statistical Learning from the very beginning. The core ideas such as bias-variance trade-off are deeply discussed and revisited in many problems. The included R examples are particularly helpful for beginners to learn R. The book also provides a brief, but concise description of functions’ parameters for many related R packages. Compared to The Elements of Statistical Learning, it is easy for the reader to understand. It does a wonderful job of breaking things down complex concepts. If one wishes to learn more about a particular topic, I’d recommend The Element of Statistical Learning. These two pair nicely together. An Introduction to Statistical Learning: with Applications in R Deep Learning This is the book to read on deep learning. Written by luminaries in the field — if you’ve read any papers on deep learning, you must have heard about Goodfellow and Bengio before — and cutting through much of the BS surrounding the topic: like ‘big data’ before it, ‘deep learning’ is not something new and is not deserving of a special name. Networks with more hidden layers to detect higher-order features, networks of different types chained together in order to play to their strengths, graphs of networks to represent a probabilistic model. This is a theoretical book, but it can be read in tandem with Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn and TensorFlow, almost chapter-for-chapter. The Scikit-Learn and Tensorflow example code, while only moderately interesting on its own, helps to clarify the purpose of many of the topics in the Goodfellow book. Deep Learning Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn and TensorFlow This book provides a great introduction to machine learning for both developer and non-developers. Authors suggest to just go through even if you don’t understand math details. Highlights of this book are: Extraction of field expert knowledge is very important, you should know which model will serve better for the given solution. Luckily, a lot of models are available already from other scientists. Training data is the most important part, the more you have it the better. So if you can you should accumulate as much data as you can, preferably categorized, you may not still know how you will apply the accumulated data in the future but you will need it. Labelling training data is very important too, to train neural network you need to have at least thousands of labelled data samples, the more the better. Machine learning algorithms and neural networks are pretty common for years but the latest breakthrough is possible because of new optimization, new autoencoders ( that may help to artificially generate training data) allowing to do training faster and with fewer data. Machine learning is still pretty time and resources consuming process. To train a machine learning model you need to know how to tweak parameters and how to use different training approaches fitting the particular model. The book demonstrates (including the code) different approaches using Scikit-Learn python package and also the TensorFlow. Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow Data Science for Business This is probably the most practical book to read if you are looking for an overview of data science. Either you know when terms like k-means and ROC curves are to be used or you have some context when you start digging deeper into how some of these algorithms are implemented. You will find it at the right level because there is just enough math to explain the fundamental concepts and make them stick in your head. This isn’t a book on implementing these concepts or a bunch of algorithms. This gives the book the advantage of being something you can refer to an intelligent manager or interested developer, and they can both get a lot out of it. And if they are interested in the next level of learning there are plenty of pointers. You will also find the chapter on presenting results through ROC curves, lift curves, etc. pretty interesting. It would be cool if this book had some more hands-on, but you can go to Kaggle and browse around the current and past competitions to apply what you learn here. Data Science for Business Courses to attend Machine Learning Machine Learning is one of the first programming MOOCs. Coursera put online by Coursera founder and Stanford Professor Andrew Ng. This course assumes that you have basic programming skills and you have some understanding of Linear Algebra. Knowledge of Statistics &amp;amp; Probability is not required though. Andrew Ng does a good job explaining dense material and slides. The course gives you a lot of structure and direction for each homework, so it is generally pretty clear what you are supposed to do and how you are supposed to do it. Machine Learning by Andrew Ng Deep Learning When you are rather new to the topic, you can learn a lot of doing the deeplearning.ai specialization. First and foremost, you learn the basic concepts of NN. How does a forward pass in simple sequential models look like, what’s a backpropagation, and so on? I experienced this set of courses as a very time-effective way to learn the basics and worth more than all the tutorials, blog posts and talks, which I went through beforehand. Doing this specialization is probably more than the first step into DL. I would say, each course is a single step in the right direction, so you end up with five steps in total. I think it builds a fundamental understanding of the field. But going further, you have to practice a lot and eventually it might be useful also to read more about the methodological background of DL variants. But doing the course work gets you started in a structured manner — which is worth a lot, especially in a field with so much buzz around it. Deep Learning Specialization Fast AI If your goal is to be able to learn about deep learning and apply what you’ve learned, the fast.ai course is a better bet. If you have the time, interleaving the deeplearning.ai and fast.ai courses is ideal — you get the practical experience, applicability, and audience interaction of fast.ai, along with the organised material and theoretical explanations of deeplearning.ai. Fast AI Course Kaggle Learn Practical data skills you can apply immediately: that’s what you’ll learn in these free micro-courses. They’re the fastest (and most fun) way to become a data scientist or improve your current skills. Kaggle Learn Blogs to follow KD Nuggets KDnuggets is a leading site on AI, Analytics, Big Data, Data Mining, Data Science, and Machine Learning and is edited by Gregory Piatetsky-Shapiro and Matthew Mayo. KDnuggets was founded in February of 1997. Before that, Gregory maintained an earlier version of this site, called Knowledge Discovery Mine, at GTE Labs (1994 to 1997). KD Nuggets Analytics Vidhya Analytics Vidhya provides a community-based knowledge portal for Analytics and AI professionals. The aim of the platform is to become a complete portal serving all knowledge and career needs of Data Science Professionals. Analytics Vidhya Towards Data Science TDS joined Medium’s vibrant community in October 2016. In the beginning, their goal was simply to gather good posts and distribute them to a broader audience. Just a few months later, they were pleased to see that they had a very fast-growing audience and many new contributors. Today they are working with more than 10 Editorial Associates to prepare the most exciting content for our audience. They provide customized feedback to our contributors using Medium’s private notes. This allows them to promote their latest articles across social media without the added complexity that they might encounter using another platform. Towards Data Science Podcasts to listen Data Hack This is Analytics Vidhya’s exclusive podcast series which will feature top leaders and practitioners in the artificial intelligence and machine learning industry. So in every episode of DataHack Radio, they bring you discussions with one such thought leader in the industry. They have discussions about their journey, their learnings and plenty of other AI-related things. Data Hack Super Data Science Kirill Eremenko is a Data Science coach and lifestyle entrepreneur. The goal of the Super Data Science podcast is to bring you the most inspiring Data Scientists and Analysts from around the World to help you build your successful career in Data Science. Data is growing exponentially and so are salaries of those who work in analytics. This podcast can help you learn how to skyrocket your analytics career. Big Data, visualization, predictive modelling, forecasting, analysis, business processes, statistics, R, Python, SQL programming, tableau, machine learning, Hadoop, databases, data science MBAs, and all the analytics tools and skills that will help you better understand how to crush it in Data Science. Super Data Science The O’Reilly Data Show Podcast Known as the father of all other data shows, “the O’Reilly Data Show” features Ben Lorica, O’Reilly Media’s chief data scientist. Lorica conducts interviews with other experts about big data and data science current affairs. While it does get technical and may not be the best place for a beginner to start, it provides interesting insights into the future of the AI/ML industry. Data Show YouTube Channels DeepLearning.TV DeepLearning.TV is all about Deep Learning, the field of study that teaches machines to perceive the world. Starting with a series that simplifies Deep Learning, the channel features topics such as How To’s, reviews of software libraries and applications, and interviews with key individuals in the field. Through a series of concept videos showcasing the intuition behind every Deep Learning method, they show you that Deep Learning is actually simpler than you think. Their goal is to improve your understanding of the topic so that you can better utilize Deep Learning in your own projects. They provide a window into the cutting edge of Deep Learning and bring you up to speed on what’s currently happening in the field. DeepLearning.TV Data School Are you trying to learn data science so that you can get your first data science job? You’re probably confused about what you’re “supposed” to learn, and then you have the hardest time actually finding lessons you can understand! Data School focuses you on the topics you need to master first, and offers in-depth tutorials that you can understand regardless of your educational background. Your host here is Kevin Markham, and he is the founder of Data School. He has taught data science using the Python programming language to hundreds of students in the classroom, and hundreds of thousands of students (like you) online. Finding the right teacher was so important to his data science education, and so he sincerely hopes that he can be the right data science teacher for you. Data School Caltech Machine Learning This is an introductory course by Caltech Professor Yaser Abu-Mostafa on machine learning that covers the basic theory, algorithms, and applications. Machine learning (ML) enables computational systems to adaptively improve their performance with experience accumulated from the observed data. ML techniques are widely applied in engineering, science, finance, and commerce to build systems for which we do not have a full mathematical specification (and that covers a lot of systems). The course balances theory and practice and covers the mathematical as well as the heuristic aspects. Caltech Machine Learning GitHub Repos Awesome Data Science This Repo answer the questions, “What is Data Science and what should you study to learn Data Science?” An awesome Data Science repository to learn and apply for real-world problems. As the aggregator says, “Our favourite data scientist is Clare Corthell. She is an expert in data-related systems and a hacker and has been working on a company as a data scientist. Clare’s blog. This website helps you to understand the exact way to study as a professional data scientist.” “Secondly, Our favourite programming language is Python nowadays for Data Science. Python’s — Pandas library has full functionality for collecting and analyzing data. We use Anaconda to play with data and to create applications.” Awesome Data Science Essential Cheat Sheets for Machine Learning and Deep Learning Engineers Machine learning is complex. For newbies, starting to learn machine learning can be painful if they don’t have the right resources to learn from. Most of the machine learning libraries are difficult to understand and the learning curve can be a bit frustrating. Kailash Ahirwar has created a repository on Github (cheatsheets-ai) containing cheatsheets for different machine learning frameworks, gathered from different sources. Have a look at the Github repository, also, contribute cheat sheets if you have any. Thanks. Essential Cheat Sheets HackerMath for Machine Learning Math literacy, including proficiency in Linear Algebra and Statistics, is a must for anyone pursuing a career in data science. The goal of this workshop is to introduce some key concepts from these domains that get used repeatedly in data science/AI applications. As outlined by Amit Kapoor, “Our approach is what we call the ‘Hacker’s way’. Instead of going back to formulae and proofs, we teach the concepts by writing code. And in practical applications. Concepts don’t remain sticky if the usage is never taught.” The focus here is on depth rather than breadth. Three areas are chosen — Hypothesis Testing, Supervised Learning and Unsupervised Learning. They are covered to sufficient depth — 50% of the time on the concepts and 50% of the time spent coding them. HackerMath for Machine Learning So this is all that I needed to cover in this article. Now you know what useful resources you need to keep handy in order to get proficient in the field of AI. Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on YouTube, Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Title</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/2020/02/14/DataScience_Pipeline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Title" /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/2020/02/14/DataScience_Pipeline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/2020/02/14/DataScience_Pipeline.html">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-02-14-DataScience_Pipeline.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# import basic libraries&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;warnings&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;warnings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filterwarnings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;ignore&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# import plot libraries&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;set_palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Set2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;matplotlib&lt;/span&gt; inline

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# import ml libraries&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.metrics&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;confusion_matrix&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.preprocessing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LabelEncoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MinMaxScaler&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.model_selection&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train_test_split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cross_val_score&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linear_model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;datasets&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.ensemble&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;RandomForestClassifier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;RandomForestRegressor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.metrics&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accuracy_score&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.svm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LinearSVC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SVC&lt;/span&gt;



&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# categories v1, v4, v8, v9, v11, v12, v16, classLabel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;sklearn.preprocessing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LabelEncoder&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LabelEncoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# list number of files&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;listdir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;data&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# import data&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;ls&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;../input/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;decode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;utf8&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;data/train.csv&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;test&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;data/test.csv&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# check shape&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Train rows and columns : &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Test rows and columns : &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# check column types&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctype&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dtypes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reset_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Count&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Column Type&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;groupby&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Column Type&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;aggregate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;count&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reset_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# display data&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# numerical data distribution&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;describe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# categorical data distribution&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;describe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;O&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# check missing values&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isnull&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reset_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;column_name&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;missing_count&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;missing_count&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sort_values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;missing_count&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;missing_df&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# impute/treat missing values&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fillna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value_counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for categorical&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fillna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for numerical (mean or median)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# check ouliers&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# upper outliers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# lower outliers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# treat outliers&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# treat upper outliers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fmean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fstd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# treat lower outliers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# univariate analysis&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# histogram of numerical column&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;figsize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;num&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;kde&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xlabel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;num&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fontsize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;num histogram&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fontsize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# charts of categorical column&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value_counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sizes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;col&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value_counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# pie plot for categorical column&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subplots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sizes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;labels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;autopct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;%1.1f%%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shadow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;equal&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# bar plot for categorical column&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fig2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subplots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;countplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;col&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# bivariate analysis&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cat1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cat2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# categorical vs categorical&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;violinplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;num&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# categorical vs numerical&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;regplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;num1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;num2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# numerical vs numerical&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# multivariate analysis &lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;temp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cols_to_use&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;corrmat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;temp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;corr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;spearman&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subplots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;figsize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;heatmap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;corrmat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;vmax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;square&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;YlGnBu&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;annot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;numerical variables correlation map&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fontsize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# split data&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;target&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train_test_split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;random_state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;123&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# feature engineering on train/valid&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LabelEncoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit_transform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for categorical data&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scaler&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MinMaxScaler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for numerical data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scaler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;                      
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scaler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;transform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scaler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;transform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# build model on train&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linear_model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LogisticRegression&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;1e5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# RandomForestClassifier(), SVC(), RandomForestRegressor() etc&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_pred&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;predict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# evaluate on valid&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;confusion_matrix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_pred&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for categorical target&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean_squared_error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_pred&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for numerical target&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# k-fold cross-validation&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;svm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SVC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;kernel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;linear&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cross_val_score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Score: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;%0.2f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt; (+/- &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;%0.2f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;                   
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# hyper-parameter tuning&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gamma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.001&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.001&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# for each combination of parameters,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# train an SVC&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;svm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SVC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gamma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gamma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# perform cross-validation&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cross_val_score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;svm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# compute mean cross-validation accuracy&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# if we got a better score, store the score and parameters&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;best_score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;best_score&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;best_parameters&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;C&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;gamma&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gamma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# rebuild a model on the combined training and validation set&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;svm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SVC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;best_parameters&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;svm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;X_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;y_train&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;input&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;input_area&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot; highlight hl-ipython3&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# ensembling/stacking&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# to be continued...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Intelligence from Novice to Professional</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/01/23/artificial-intelligence-from-novice-to-professional.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Intelligence from Novice to Professional" /><published>2020-01-23T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/01/23/artificial-intelligence-from-novice-to-professional</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2020/01/23/artificial-intelligence-from-novice-to-professional.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*PNtNefJMXMdi0JwUA2YWRA.png&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Ben White](https://unsplash.com/@benwhitephotography?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)/[Hunters Race](https://unsplash.com/@huntersrace?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/s/photos/faceless-person?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-thispost&quot;&gt;Why this post?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a general notion that Artificial Intelligence is all about algorithms. If you look around most of the courses, books, blogs, etc, you will find that most of them cover how you can apply certain algorithms and further optimize those algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working on a few real-world AI/ML projects, you will realize that while algorithms are at the core, AI is much more than algorithms. From identifying &amp;amp; assessing AI opportunities in your organization/department to deploying and maintaining the solutions in production, a lot goes into AI/ML projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I am going to briefly touch every aspect of AI/ML project lifecycle. The good news is, as a data scientist you need not master every aspect, but knowing those areas to some extent will help you contribute better in real-world projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A single post can’t make you an AI professional, but it can ask relevant questions &amp;amp; increase awareness, seeking answers to these questions can help you build your own AI roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can segregate all these aspects of AI into 5 parts: AI Introduction, AI Pre-requisites, AI Concepts &amp;amp; Algorithms, Enterprise AI &amp;amp; Peripherals of AI&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-ai-introduction&quot;&gt;I. AI Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is a team game, every aspiring AI role needs to have a common understanding of AI/ML field. This part covers a simple What, Why &amp;amp; How of AI:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Why you should learn AI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Why AI is important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— What is Artificial Intelligence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— How an end-to-end AI project looks like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— What are the roles in AI projects and who does what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ii-ai-pre-requisites&quot;&gt;II. AI Pre-requisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI/ML has a steep learning curve because it is an amalgamation of many fields (Statistics, IT &amp;amp; Domain etc). And some knowledge of these fields is required before you can start grasping AI/ML concepts. This part covers the pre-requisites of AI:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— What topics of maths you should cover?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— What programming languages, libraries &amp;amp; frameworks you should be aware of?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— How does data move in an organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— How is it stored and processed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iii-ai-concepts--algorithms&quot;&gt;III. AI Concepts &amp;amp; Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI/ML in itself is quite a vast field and have different techniques and frameworks to deal with different kind of real-world problems. This part covers major AI/ML techniques and what to use when:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— What are the major types of AI techniques?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— When to use what? Main concepts &amp;amp; algorithms ML, DL &amp;amp; RL?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iv-enterprise-ai&quot;&gt;IV. Enterprise AI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning AI/ML concepts &amp;amp; algorithms are not enough, you will be solving some business problems with what you have learned. You need to be aware of what happens when these concepts &amp;amp; algorithms are applied within an enterprise. This part covers the aspects of enterprise AI:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- What is the difference between Hackathons &amp;amp; Real-world projects?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- How to operationalize AI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- How to build AI Strategy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- Why ethics &amp;amp; explainability is important &amp;amp; how can we make AI explainable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;v-peripherals-ofai&quot;&gt;V. Peripherals of AI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from learning concepts and their applications, you may have specific needs at the moment like you want to get into the AI field or you need to lead an AI initiative in your organization. This part covers those specific needs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- How you can get into AI field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- How to lead AI initiatives in your organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;- How to future-proof your AI career?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope by now you have got an idea of what it takes to work on AI projects in the real world. Due to different but overlapping fields, it is really hard to get in-depth knowledge of every aspect of an AI aspirant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what you can do is to build a T-shape skill-set in the AI field, where you go in-depth in the aspect of your choice and have handy knowledge of other related aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will cover the above-mentioned aspects of AI thoroughly in upcoming posts, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCrIv4EU2tFX8VhhT0oCnDnw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why this post? There is a general notion that Artificial Intelligence is all about algorithms. If you look around most of the courses, books, blogs, etc, you will find that most of them cover how you can apply certain algorithms and further optimize those algorithms. After working on a few real-world AI/ML projects, you will realize that while algorithms are at the core, AI is much more than algorithms. From identifying &amp;amp; assessing AI opportunities in your organization/department to deploying and maintaining the solutions in production, a lot goes into AI/ML projects. In this post, I am going to briefly touch every aspect of AI/ML project lifecycle. The good news is, as a data scientist you need not master every aspect, but knowing those areas to some extent will help you contribute better in real-world projects. A single post can’t make you an AI professional, but it can ask relevant questions &amp;amp; increase awareness, seeking answers to these questions can help you build your own AI roadmap. We can segregate all these aspects of AI into 5 parts: AI Introduction, AI Pre-requisites, AI Concepts &amp;amp; Algorithms, Enterprise AI &amp;amp; Peripherals of AI I. AI Introduction AI is a team game, every aspiring AI role needs to have a common understanding of AI/ML field. This part covers a simple What, Why &amp;amp; How of AI: — Why you should learn AI? — Why AI is important? — What is Artificial Intelligence? — How an end-to-end AI project looks like? — What are the roles in AI projects and who does what? II. AI Pre-requisites AI/ML has a steep learning curve because it is an amalgamation of many fields (Statistics, IT &amp;amp; Domain etc). And some knowledge of these fields is required before you can start grasping AI/ML concepts. This part covers the pre-requisites of AI: — What topics of maths you should cover? — What programming languages, libraries &amp;amp; frameworks you should be aware of? — How does data move in an organization? — How is it stored and processed? III. AI Concepts &amp;amp; Algorithms AI/ML in itself is quite a vast field and have different techniques and frameworks to deal with different kind of real-world problems. This part covers major AI/ML techniques and what to use when: — What are the major types of AI techniques? — When to use what? Main concepts &amp;amp; algorithms ML, DL &amp;amp; RL? IV. Enterprise AI Learning AI/ML concepts &amp;amp; algorithms are not enough, you will be solving some business problems with what you have learned. You need to be aware of what happens when these concepts &amp;amp; algorithms are applied within an enterprise. This part covers the aspects of enterprise AI: - What is the difference between Hackathons &amp;amp; Real-world projects? - How to operationalize AI? - How to build AI Strategy? - Why ethics &amp;amp; explainability is important &amp;amp; how can we make AI explainable? V. Peripherals of AI Apart from learning concepts and their applications, you may have specific needs at the moment like you want to get into the AI field or you need to lead an AI initiative in your organization. This part covers those specific needs: - How you can get into AI field? - How to lead AI initiatives in your organization? - How to future-proof your AI career? Conclusion I hope by now you have got an idea of what it takes to work on AI projects in the real world. Due to different but overlapping fields, it is really hard to get in-depth knowledge of every aspect of an AI aspirant. But what you can do is to build a T-shape skill-set in the AI field, where you go in-depth in the aspect of your choice and have handy knowledge of other related aspects. I will cover the above-mentioned aspects of AI thoroughly in upcoming posts, stay tuned. Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on YouTube, Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Blocks of Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/27/building-blocks-of-artificial-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Blocks of Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2019-12-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/27/building-blocks-of-artificial-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/27/building-blocks-of-artificial-intelligence.html">&lt;p&gt;Title: Building Blocks of Artificial Intelligence
Date: 2019-12-27 17:10
Author: ankitrathi
Category: Uncategorized
Tags: Artificial Intelligence, Building Blocks, Data Science, Machine Learning, Towards Data Science
Slug: building-blocks-of-artificial-intelligence
Status: published&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*jQQ7PSA9MQXa0FTdS19EHA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few core skills in every job. To perform that job, you need to be aware of core concepts, you need to be aware of the end to end process and you need to learn how to use related tools to perform that job. Artificial Intelligence is no different, it has its own core concepts, processes and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post covers the core concepts you need to learn, the end-to-end process you need to be aware of &amp;amp; important tools you need to master to work as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*rhRKmQu9vXKYuzHOftQ05Q.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please note that this post only outlines the concepts, processes and tools used by data scientists. I will publish the resources (mostly free) for these topics in upcoming post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concepts-tolearn&quot;&gt;Concepts to learn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*IQdUsr1L1EjjGRJTVxXzlw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mathematics&quot;&gt;Mathematics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence contains math — no avoiding that! This section is for learners about basic math they need in order to be successful in almost any AI project/problem. So let’s start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multivariate Calculus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculus is a set of tools for analyzing the relationship between functions and their inputs. In Multivariate Calculus, we can take a function with multiple inputs and determine the influence of each of them separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In AI, we try to find the inputs which enable a function to best match the data. The slope or descent describes the rate of change off the output with respect to an input. Determining the influence of each input on the output is also one of the critical tasks. All this requires a solid understanding of Multivariate Calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linear Algebra&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;algebra&lt;/em&gt; comes from the Arabi word “&lt;em&gt;al-jabr&lt;/em&gt;” which means “&lt;em&gt;the reunion of broken parts&lt;/em&gt;”. This is the collection of methods deriving unknowns from knowns in mathematics. &lt;em&gt;Linear Algebra&lt;/em&gt; is the branch that deals with &lt;em&gt;linear equations&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;linear functions&lt;/em&gt; which are represented through &lt;em&gt;matrices&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vectors&lt;/em&gt;. In simpler words, it helps us understand geometric terms such as planes, in higher dimensions, and perform mathematical operations on them. By definition, algebra deals primarily with scalars (one-dimensional entities), but Linear Algebra has vectors and matrices (entities which possess two or more dimensional components) to deal with linear equations and functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linear Algebra&lt;/em&gt; is central to almost all areas of mathematics like &lt;em&gt;geometry&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;functional analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Its concepts are a crucial prerequisite for understanding the theory behind &lt;em&gt;AI&lt;/em&gt;. You don’t need to understand &lt;em&gt;Linear Algebra&lt;/em&gt; before getting started in &lt;em&gt;AI&lt;/em&gt;, but at some point, you may want to gain a better understanding of how the &lt;em&gt;different algorithms&lt;/em&gt; really work under the hood. So if you really want to be a professional in this field, you will have to master the parts of &lt;em&gt;Linear Algebra&lt;/em&gt; that are important for &lt;em&gt;AI&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statistics &amp;amp; Probability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statistics&lt;/em&gt; is a mathematical body of science that pertains to the &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;analysis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;interpretation&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;presentation&lt;/em&gt; of data. Probability is the chance that something will happen — how likely it is that some event will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics help you to understand your data and is an initial &amp;amp; very important step of AI. This is due to the fact that AI is all about making predictions and you can’t predict if you can’t understand the patterns in existing data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty and randomness occur in many aspects of our daily life and having a good knowledge of probability helps us make sense of these uncertainties. Learning about probability helps us make informed judgments on what is likely to happen, based on a pattern of data collected previously or an estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI often uses statistical inferences to predict or analyze trends from data, while statistical inferences use probability distributions of data. Hence knowing probability &amp;amp; statistics and its applications are important to work effectively on AI problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming&quot;&gt;Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To execute the AI pipeline, you need to learn algorithm design as well as fundamental programming concepts such as data selection, iteration and functional decomposition, data abstraction and organisation. In addition to this, you need to learn how to perform simple data visualizations using programming and embed your learning using problem-based assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning-algorithms&quot;&gt;Machine Learning Algorithms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning algorithms can be divided into 3 broad categories —&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supervised learning,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsupervised learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supervised learning is useful in cases where a property (&lt;em&gt;label&lt;/em&gt;) is available for a certain dataset (&lt;em&gt;training set&lt;/em&gt;) but is missing and needs to be predicted for other instances. Unsupervised learning is useful in cases where the challenge is to discover implicit relationships in a given &lt;em&gt;unlabeled&lt;/em&gt; dataset (items are not pre-assigned). Reinforcement learning falls between these 2 extremes — there is some form of feedback available for each predictive step or action, but no precise label or error message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Intrinsic details of various algorithms is not in scope of this series, you can refer the resources mentioned in the next post to learn them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supervised learning can be further divided into Regression (Linear, Non-linear, etc) &amp;amp; Classification (Logistics Regression, Decision Tree, Naïve Bayes etc) algorithms. Some algorithms can be used for regression as well as classification i.e. Random Forests, Support Vector Machines, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsupervised learning can also be further divided into Clustering, Anomaly Detection, Associative Mining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning is an area of machine learning concerned with how software agents ought to take actions in an environment so as to maximize some notion of cumulative reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-learning-frameworks&quot;&gt;Deep Learning Frameworks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning frameworks are a more advanced form of ML and solve specific problems where data is either unstructured or huge or both. Neural Nets, CNNs, RNNs &amp;amp; LSTM, GANs are the frameworks one needs to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;domain-knowledge&quot;&gt;Domain Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of domain knowledge, while perfectly understandable, can be a major barrier to data scientists. For one thing, it’s difficult to come up with project ideas in a domain that you don’t know much about. It can also be difficult to determine the type of data that may be helpful for a project — if you want to build a model to predict an outcome, you need to know what types of variables might be related to this outcome so you can make sure to gather the right data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing the domain is useful not only for figuring out projects and how to approach them but also for having rules of thumb for sanity checks on the data. Knowing how data is captured (is it hand-entered? Is it from machines that can give false readings for any number of reasons?) can help a data scientist with data cleaning and from going too far down the wrong path. It can also inform what true outliers are and which values might just be due to measurement error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often the most challenging part of building a machine learning model is feature engineering. Understanding variables and how they relate to an outcome is extremely important for this. Knowing the domain can help direct the data exploration and greatly speed (and enhance) the feature engineering process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once features are generated, knowing what relationships between variables are plausible help for basic sanity checks. Being able to glance at the outcome of a model and determine if they make sense goes a long way for quality assurance of any analytical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the biggest reasons a strong understanding of the data is important is because you have to interpret the results of analyses and modeling work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what results are important and which are trivial is important for the presentation and communication of results. It’s also important to know what results are actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;process-tofollow&quot;&gt;Process to follow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*TPtwP0mAlx6JGjSiJCy18g.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-definition&quot;&gt;Problem Definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you have to do before you solve a problem is to define exactly what it is. You need to be able to translate data questions into something actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll often get ambiguous inputs from the people who have problems. You’ll have to develop the intuition to turn scarce inputs into actionable outputs–and to ask the questions that nobody else is asking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-collection&quot;&gt;Data Collection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve defined the problem, you’ll need data to give you the insights needed to turn the problem around with a solution. This part of the process involves thinking through what data you’ll need and finding ways to get that data, whether it’s querying internal databases, or purchasing external data-sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-understanding&quot;&gt;Data Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty here isn’t coming up with ideas to test, it’s coming up with ideas that are likely to turn into insights. You’ll have a fixed deadline for your AI project, so you’ll have to prioritize your questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll have to look at some of the most interesting patterns that can help explain why sales are reduced for this group. You might notice that they don’t tend to be very active on social media, with few of them having Twitter or Facebook accounts. You might also notice that most of them are older than your general audience. From that you can begin to trace patterns you can analyze more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feature-engineering&quot;&gt;Feature Engineering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feature engineering is the process of using domain knowledge of the data to create features that make machine learning algorithms work. If feature engineering is done correctly, it increases the predictive power of machine learning algorithms by creating features from raw data that help facilitate the machine learning process. Feature Engineering is, in fact, an art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modelling&quot;&gt;Modelling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the type of question that you’re trying to answer, there are many modelling algorithms available. You run the selected algorithm/s on the training data to build the models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;validation&quot;&gt;Validation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Validation is a step used to evaluate the trained model on validation data. You use a series of competing for machine-learning algorithms along with the various associated tuning parameters that are geared toward answering the question of interest with the current data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tuning&quot;&gt;Tuning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuning an algorithm or machine learning technique can be simply thought of as a process which one goes through in which they optimize the parameters that impact the model in order to enable the algorithm to perform the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deployment&quot;&gt;Deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you have a set of models that perform well, you can operationalize them for other applications to consume. Depending on the business requirements, predictions are made either in real-time or on a batch basis. To deploy models, you expose them with an open API interface. The interface enables the model to be easily consumed from various applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-tomaster&quot;&gt;Tools to master&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Y0AVQ5pq0t0NKEec9AXxZQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The list mentioned here is not exhaustive, it depends more on what kind of problem you are solving and in what tech stack you are working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sql&quot;&gt;SQL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structured Query Language (SQL) is a standard computer language for relational database management and data manipulation. SQL is used to query, insert, update and modify data. Most relational databases support SQL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As data collection has increased exponentially, so has the need for people skilled at using and interacting with data; to be able to think critically, and provide insights to make better decisions and optimize their businesses. The skills necessary to be a good data scientist include being able to retrieve and work with data and to do that you need to be well versed in SQL, the standard language for communicating with database systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;r&quot;&gt;R&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R is a programming language and software environment for statistical analysis, graphics representation and reporting. In the world of AI, R is an increasingly popular language for a reason. It was built with statistical manipulation in mind, and there’s an incredible ecosystem of packages for R that let you do amazing things — particularly in data visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;python&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is a general-purpose interpreted, interactive, object-oriented, and high-level programming language. Python is no-doubt the best-suited language for a Data Scientist. It is a free, flexible and powerful open-source language. Python cuts development time in half with its simple and easy to read syntax. With Python, you can perform data manipulation, analysis, and visualization. Python provides powerful libraries for Machine learning applications and other scientific computations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tensorflow&quot;&gt;Tensorflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the most famous deep learning library in the world is Google’s TensorFlow. Google product uses machine learning in all of its products to improve the search engine, translation, image captioning or recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TensorFlow is the best library of all because it is built to be accessible to everyone. Tensorflow library incorporates different API to built at scale deep learning architecture like CNN or RNN. TensorFlow is based on graph computation; it allows the developer to visualize the construction of the neural network with Tensorboad. This tool is helpful to debug the program. Finally, Tensorflow is built to be deployed at scale. It runs on CPU and GPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keras&quot;&gt;Keras&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keras is a high-level neural networks API, capable of running on top of Tensorflow, Theano, and CNTK. It enables fast experimentation through a high level, user-friendly, modular and extensible API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keras allows for easy and fast prototyping (through user-friendliness, modularity, and extensibility). It supports both convolutional networks and recurrent networks, as well as combinations of the two. It runs seamlessly on CPU and GPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is all that I needed to cover in this article. Now you know what concepts you need to learn, the process you need to follow and the tools you need to master in order to get proficient in the field of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Title: Building Blocks of Artificial Intelligence Date: 2019-12-27 17:10 Author: ankitrathi Category: Uncategorized Tags: Artificial Intelligence, Building Blocks, Data Science, Machine Learning, Towards Data Science Slug: building-blocks-of-artificial-intelligence Status: published There are a few core skills in every job. To perform that job, you need to be aware of core concepts, you need to be aware of the end to end process and you need to learn how to use related tools to perform that job. Artificial Intelligence is no different, it has its own core concepts, processes and tools. This post covers the core concepts you need to learn, the end-to-end process you need to be aware of &amp;amp; important tools you need to master to work as a data scientist. Please note that this post only outlines the concepts, processes and tools used by data scientists. I will publish the resources (mostly free) for these topics in upcoming post. Concepts to learn Mathematics Artificial Intelligence contains math — no avoiding that! This section is for learners about basic math they need in order to be successful in almost any AI project/problem. So let’s start: Multivariate Calculus Calculus is a set of tools for analyzing the relationship between functions and their inputs. In Multivariate Calculus, we can take a function with multiple inputs and determine the influence of each of them separately. In AI, we try to find the inputs which enable a function to best match the data. The slope or descent describes the rate of change off the output with respect to an input. Determining the influence of each input on the output is also one of the critical tasks. All this requires a solid understanding of Multivariate Calculus. Linear Algebra The word algebra comes from the Arabi word “al-jabr” which means “the reunion of broken parts”. This is the collection of methods deriving unknowns from knowns in mathematics. Linear Algebra is the branch that deals with linear equations and linear functions which are represented through matrices and vectors. In simpler words, it helps us understand geometric terms such as planes, in higher dimensions, and perform mathematical operations on them. By definition, algebra deals primarily with scalars (one-dimensional entities), but Linear Algebra has vectors and matrices (entities which possess two or more dimensional components) to deal with linear equations and functions. Linear Algebra is central to almost all areas of mathematics like geometry and functional analysis. Its concepts are a crucial prerequisite for understanding the theory behind AI. You don’t need to understand Linear Algebra before getting started in AI, but at some point, you may want to gain a better understanding of how the different algorithms really work under the hood. So if you really want to be a professional in this field, you will have to master the parts of Linear Algebra that are important for AI. Statistics &amp;amp; Probability Statistics is a mathematical body of science that pertains to the collection, analysis, interpretation or explanation, and presentation of data. Probability is the chance that something will happen — how likely it is that some event will happen. Statistics help you to understand your data and is an initial &amp;amp; very important step of AI. This is due to the fact that AI is all about making predictions and you can’t predict if you can’t understand the patterns in existing data. Uncertainty and randomness occur in many aspects of our daily life and having a good knowledge of probability helps us make sense of these uncertainties. Learning about probability helps us make informed judgments on what is likely to happen, based on a pattern of data collected previously or an estimate. AI often uses statistical inferences to predict or analyze trends from data, while statistical inferences use probability distributions of data. Hence knowing probability &amp;amp; statistics and its applications are important to work effectively on AI problems. Programming To execute the AI pipeline, you need to learn algorithm design as well as fundamental programming concepts such as data selection, iteration and functional decomposition, data abstraction and organisation. In addition to this, you need to learn how to perform simple data visualizations using programming and embed your learning using problem-based assignments. Machine Learning Algorithms Machine learning algorithms can be divided into 3 broad categories — Supervised learning, Unsupervised learning Reinforcement learning. Supervised learning is useful in cases where a property (label) is available for a certain dataset (training set) but is missing and needs to be predicted for other instances. Unsupervised learning is useful in cases where the challenge is to discover implicit relationships in a given unlabeled dataset (items are not pre-assigned). Reinforcement learning falls between these 2 extremes — there is some form of feedback available for each predictive step or action, but no precise label or error message. Intrinsic details of various algorithms is not in scope of this series, you can refer the resources mentioned in the next post to learn them. Supervised learning can be further divided into Regression (Linear, Non-linear, etc) &amp;amp; Classification (Logistics Regression, Decision Tree, Naïve Bayes etc) algorithms. Some algorithms can be used for regression as well as classification i.e. Random Forests, Support Vector Machines, etc. Unsupervised learning can also be further divided into Clustering, Anomaly Detection, Associative Mining. Reinforcement learning is an area of machine learning concerned with how software agents ought to take actions in an environment so as to maximize some notion of cumulative reward. Deep Learning Frameworks Deep learning frameworks are a more advanced form of ML and solve specific problems where data is either unstructured or huge or both. Neural Nets, CNNs, RNNs &amp;amp; LSTM, GANs are the frameworks one needs to be aware of. Domain Knowledge This lack of domain knowledge, while perfectly understandable, can be a major barrier to data scientists. For one thing, it’s difficult to come up with project ideas in a domain that you don’t know much about. It can also be difficult to determine the type of data that may be helpful for a project — if you want to build a model to predict an outcome, you need to know what types of variables might be related to this outcome so you can make sure to gather the right data. Knowing the domain is useful not only for figuring out projects and how to approach them but also for having rules of thumb for sanity checks on the data. Knowing how data is captured (is it hand-entered? Is it from machines that can give false readings for any number of reasons?) can help a data scientist with data cleaning and from going too far down the wrong path. It can also inform what true outliers are and which values might just be due to measurement error. Often the most challenging part of building a machine learning model is feature engineering. Understanding variables and how they relate to an outcome is extremely important for this. Knowing the domain can help direct the data exploration and greatly speed (and enhance) the feature engineering process. Once features are generated, knowing what relationships between variables are plausible help for basic sanity checks. Being able to glance at the outcome of a model and determine if they make sense goes a long way for quality assurance of any analytical work. Finally, one of the biggest reasons a strong understanding of the data is important is because you have to interpret the results of analyses and modeling work. Knowing what results are important and which are trivial is important for the presentation and communication of results. It’s also important to know what results are actionable. Process to follow Problem Definition The first thing you have to do before you solve a problem is to define exactly what it is. You need to be able to translate data questions into something actionable. You’ll often get ambiguous inputs from the people who have problems. You’ll have to develop the intuition to turn scarce inputs into actionable outputs–and to ask the questions that nobody else is asking. Data Collection Once you’ve defined the problem, you’ll need data to give you the insights needed to turn the problem around with a solution. This part of the process involves thinking through what data you’ll need and finding ways to get that data, whether it’s querying internal databases, or purchasing external data-sets. Data Understanding The difficulty here isn’t coming up with ideas to test, it’s coming up with ideas that are likely to turn into insights. You’ll have a fixed deadline for your AI project, so you’ll have to prioritize your questions. You’ll have to look at some of the most interesting patterns that can help explain why sales are reduced for this group. You might notice that they don’t tend to be very active on social media, with few of them having Twitter or Facebook accounts. You might also notice that most of them are older than your general audience. From that you can begin to trace patterns you can analyze more deeply. Feature Engineering Feature engineering is the process of using domain knowledge of the data to create features that make machine learning algorithms work. If feature engineering is done correctly, it increases the predictive power of machine learning algorithms by creating features from raw data that help facilitate the machine learning process. Feature Engineering is, in fact, an art. Modelling Depending on the type of question that you’re trying to answer, there are many modelling algorithms available. You run the selected algorithm/s on the training data to build the models. Validation Validation is a step used to evaluate the trained model on validation data. You use a series of competing for machine-learning algorithms along with the various associated tuning parameters that are geared toward answering the question of interest with the current data. Tuning Tuning an algorithm or machine learning technique can be simply thought of as a process which one goes through in which they optimize the parameters that impact the model in order to enable the algorithm to perform the best. Deployment After you have a set of models that perform well, you can operationalize them for other applications to consume. Depending on the business requirements, predictions are made either in real-time or on a batch basis. To deploy models, you expose them with an open API interface. The interface enables the model to be easily consumed from various applications. Tools to master The list mentioned here is not exhaustive, it depends more on what kind of problem you are solving and in what tech stack you are working. SQL Structured Query Language (SQL) is a standard computer language for relational database management and data manipulation. SQL is used to query, insert, update and modify data. Most relational databases support SQL. As data collection has increased exponentially, so has the need for people skilled at using and interacting with data; to be able to think critically, and provide insights to make better decisions and optimize their businesses. The skills necessary to be a good data scientist include being able to retrieve and work with data and to do that you need to be well versed in SQL, the standard language for communicating with database systems. R R is a programming language and software environment for statistical analysis, graphics representation and reporting. In the world of AI, R is an increasingly popular language for a reason. It was built with statistical manipulation in mind, and there’s an incredible ecosystem of packages for R that let you do amazing things — particularly in data visualization. Python Python is a general-purpose interpreted, interactive, object-oriented, and high-level programming language. Python is no-doubt the best-suited language for a Data Scientist. It is a free, flexible and powerful open-source language. Python cuts development time in half with its simple and easy to read syntax. With Python, you can perform data manipulation, analysis, and visualization. Python provides powerful libraries for Machine learning applications and other scientific computations. Tensorflow Currently, the most famous deep learning library in the world is Google’s TensorFlow. Google product uses machine learning in all of its products to improve the search engine, translation, image captioning or recommendations. TensorFlow is the best library of all because it is built to be accessible to everyone. Tensorflow library incorporates different API to built at scale deep learning architecture like CNN or RNN. TensorFlow is based on graph computation; it allows the developer to visualize the construction of the neural network with Tensorboad. This tool is helpful to debug the program. Finally, Tensorflow is built to be deployed at scale. It runs on CPU and GPU. Keras Keras is a high-level neural networks API, capable of running on top of Tensorflow, Theano, and CNTK. It enables fast experimentation through a high level, user-friendly, modular and extensible API. Keras allows for easy and fast prototyping (through user-friendliness, modularity, and extensibility). It supports both convolutional networks and recurrent networks, as well as combinations of the two. It runs seamlessly on CPU and GPU. So this is all that I needed to cover in this article. Now you know what concepts you need to learn, the process you need to follow and the tools you need to master in order to get proficient in the field of AI. Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Navigate Artificial Intelligence Landscape?</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/07/how-to-navigate-artificial-intelligence-landscape.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Navigate Artificial Intelligence Landscape?" /><published>2019-12-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/07/how-to-navigate-artificial-intelligence-landscape</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/12/07/how-to-navigate-artificial-intelligence-landscape.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/0*QNdQhs_T3ffa6B0m.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Rob Bates](https://unsplash.com/photos/0eLg8OTuCw0?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/search/photos/landscape?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ankitrathi.com&quot;&gt;www.ankitrathi.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a complex and evolving field. The first challenge an AI aspirant faces is understanding the landscape and how he could navigate through it. Consider this, if you are travelling to a new city, and if you don’t have the map, you will have trouble to navigate the city and you will need to ask a lot of random people during your travel without knowing how much they know about the place. Similarly, all the newcomers to AI have this trouble, and there are two ways to deal with this, arrange the map (or a guide) or travel yourself and learn with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: AI &amp;amp; DS/AI terms are used interchangeably in the article where DS means Data Science.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*QJbUB6csfF0SznF0.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post intends to serve as a map of Artificial Intelligence field.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have heard data science, machine learning, deep learning, artificial intelligence etc terminology but might not be fully aware of these terms, what to use when and how these topics are interconnected. After going through this post, you should be able to understand what is where in the AI field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multi-disciplinary-field&quot;&gt;Multi-disciplinary field&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;AI is a multidisciplinary field with sub-fields of study in Math/Statistics, CS/IT &amp;amp; Business/Domain knowledge.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math/Statistics is required to understand the data and relationship between data elements. CS/IT skills are required to process the data to generate insights. And Business or domain knowledge is required to apply above to skills in the context of a business problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*VR8Sy8nm4EcQKn_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;computer-scienceit&quot;&gt;Computer Science/IT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming is an essential skill to become a data scientist but one needs not be a hard-core programmer to learn AI. Having familiarity with basic concepts of programming will ease the process of learning AI programming tools like Python/R. These basic concepts of programming should help a candidate get a long way on the journey to pursue a career in AI as it is all about writing efficient code to analyse big data and not being a master of programming. Individuals should learn the basics of programming in Python/R (or any relevant language) before they begin to work on AI problems/projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;maths--statistics&quot;&gt;Maths &amp;amp; Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI teams have people from diverse backgrounds like chemical engineering, physics, economics, statistics, mathematics, operations research, computer science, etc. You will find many data scientists with a bachelor’s degree in statistics and machine learning but it is not a requirement to learn AI. However, having familiarity with the basic concepts of Math and Statistics like Linear Algebra, Calculus, Probability, etc. is important to learn AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;domainbusiness-knowledge&quot;&gt;Domain/Business Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the business knowledge that the data scientists would need to have would be related to the domain that the project/analysis is in. For instance, if the data scientist is working for a credit card department in a bank, it will need to understand the specific business definitions, regulations, accounting policies &amp;amp; international standards, processes etc. This is the part that is more specific to the organization the data scientist is deployed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, one thing to take care while the hiring data scientists is not to give huge preference to domain knowledge. This may severely limit the supply of AI talents to the organization. You would have a better chance of getting more value from AI by looking for those that are strong in math &amp;amp; programming, being able to convert business objectives to mathematical models. Based on my observation, this is a much more difficult skill to find or train, as compared to domain knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;various-terminologies&quot;&gt;Various Terminologies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an AI starter, you will come across many similar terminologies. First thing you need to do is to understand what each term means and where each fits in the bigger picture. Data Science, Business Intelligence, Data Mining, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Artificial Intelligence; let’s have a look at &lt;em&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt; definition for each term &amp;amp; later see how these are interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*j4Nh1WD1U0RZQCWy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-science&quot;&gt;Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data science is an interdisciplinary field that uses scientific methods, processes, algorithms and systems to extract knowledge and insights from data in various forms, both structured and unstructured, like data mining.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-intelligence&quot;&gt;Business Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Business intelligence comprises the strategies and technologies used by enterprises for the data analysis of business information. BI technologies provide historical, current and predictive views of business operations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-mining&quot;&gt;Data Mining&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data mining is the process of discovering patterns in large data sets involving methods at the intersection of machine learning, statistics, and database systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Machine learning is the scientific study of algorithms and statistical models that computer systems use to progressively improve their performance on a specific task.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-learning&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep learning is part of a broader family of machine learning methods based on learning data representations, as opposed to task-specific algorithms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;artificial-intelligence&quot;&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artificial intelligence, sometimes called machine intelligence, is intelligence demonstrated by machines, in contrast to the natural intelligence displayed by humans and other animals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interconnection&quot;&gt;Interconnection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*2oYhsUxmRbGSgZ_i.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data mining uses statistics and other programming languages to find hidden patterns in the data to explain a certain phenomenon. It helps in building a perception about the data using both math and programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning deploys data mining techniques as well as other algorithms to develop models of what is happening behind some data to forecast future outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence uses models developed by Machine Learning and other algorithms to lead to intelligent behaviour. AI is very much programming based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Mining demonstrates patterns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine Learning forecasts with models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artificial Intelligence shapes behaviours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So you see that these terms are different but still inter-connected.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roles-in-artificial-intelligence&quot;&gt;Roles in Artificial Intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before looking into the skill-set of a data scientist, let’s have a look at various roles required to work and deliver a AI project, after all, it’s a teamwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every role has its own skills that are critical to AI projects at various stages.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*zGdwTKLtbyzDuKJP.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-scientist&quot;&gt;Data Scientist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A data scientist is someone who knows how to extract meaning from and interpret data, which requires both tools and methods from statistics and machine learning. She spends a lot of time in the process of collecting, cleaning, and munging data. Domain knowledge is also an integral part of the skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machine-learningai-engineer&quot;&gt;Machine Learning/AI Engineer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning/AI engineers are sophisticated programmers who develop machines and systems that can learn and apply knowledge without specific domain requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-analyst&quot;&gt;Data Analyst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data analysts translate numbers into plain English. Every business collects data, whether it’s sales figures, market research, logistics, or transportation costs. A data analyst’s job is to take that data and use it to help companies make better business decisions. There are many different types of data analysts in the field, including operations analysts, marketing analysts, financial analysts, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-engineer&quot;&gt;Data Engineer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Engineers are responsible for the creation and maintenance of analytics infrastructure that enables almost every other function in the data world. They are responsible for the development, construction, maintenance and testing of architectures, such as databases and large-scale processing systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-architect&quot;&gt;Data Architect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data architects build complex computer database systems for companies, either for the general public or for individual companies. They work with a team that looks at the needs of the database, the data that is available and creates a blueprint for creating, testing and maintaining that data architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analytics-manager&quot;&gt;Analytics Manager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analytics manager coordinates the different tasks that must be completed by their team for an AI project. Tasks may include researching and creating effective methods to collect data, analyzing information, and recommending solutions to business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-analyst&quot;&gt;Business Analyst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI business analyst converts the business problem statement to an AI problem statement which means what data needs to be analyzed to arrive at the insights. The data would then be reviewed with the technology team and results would be delivered to the business team in the form of insights and data patterns. The business analyst should also be knowledgeable enough to apply various predictive modelling techniques and right model selection for generating insights for the problem at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quality-analyst&quot;&gt;Quality Analyst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job of quality analyst includes checking the quality of the training data-set, preparing data-sets for testing, running statistics on human-labelled data-sets, evaluating precision and recall on the resulting ML model, reporting on unexpected patterns in outputs, and implementing necessary tools to automate repetitive parts of the work. Experience in software testing with data quality or DS/ML focus, understanding of statistics, exposure to AI / Machine Learning techniques and coding proficiency in Python, are some of the skills required for the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To work on AI projects in any of the above mentioned roles, one needs to have an understanding of the core concepts at a high level but depth is required in the specific area you would be working in.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;academia-vsindustry&quot;&gt;Academia Vs Industry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academia and Industry are different fields with different people and culture. People working in Academia for longer tenure may find it difficult to adjust to industry culture and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is also an academic trap when your career trajectory is so specialized for academia that you’re unprepared for a job outside of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The academic trap happens in all areas of study, but for this post, we focus only on AI students who want to leave academia for AI positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*JcUnrkHu2ns0P2ug.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, companies are often hesitant to hire people coming straight from academia for various reasons like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In academia, individuals prefer writing papers over internships, making grants over learning programming languages, and not doing the things that could help you in the industry but not academia. The things that are important for academic hirings, such as papers, talks, and grants, are not as important in the industry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working as a data scientist within a corporation requires an understanding of how the business world works, including how quickly deliverable need to be made, how to craft a good presentation, and how to word an email to make a request.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In academia, you are encouraged to find the most innovative and elegant solution. In industry, you are encouraged to spend as little time as possible to find an analytical solution that just fits the need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salary expectations for advanced degree holders are higher than someone with only an undergraduate degree. This also pushes away recruiters as the industry works in a different way, culture is simply different than the academic one. People coming from academia need to learn these lessons at their first job, which means that there is a lot of risk for the hiring company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Want to learn more? visit www.ankitrathi.com Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a complex and evolving field. The first challenge an AI aspirant faces is understanding the landscape and how he could navigate through it. Consider this, if you are travelling to a new city, and if you don’t have the map, you will have trouble to navigate the city and you will need to ask a lot of random people during your travel without knowing how much they know about the place. Similarly, all the newcomers to AI have this trouble, and there are two ways to deal with this, arrange the map (or a guide) or travel yourself and learn with experience. Note: AI &amp;amp; DS/AI terms are used interchangeably in the article where DS means Data Science. This post intends to serve as a map of Artificial Intelligence field. You might have heard data science, machine learning, deep learning, artificial intelligence etc terminology but might not be fully aware of these terms, what to use when and how these topics are interconnected. After going through this post, you should be able to understand what is where in the AI field. Multi-disciplinary field AI is a multidisciplinary field with sub-fields of study in Math/Statistics, CS/IT &amp;amp; Business/Domain knowledge. Math/Statistics is required to understand the data and relationship between data elements. CS/IT skills are required to process the data to generate insights. And Business or domain knowledge is required to apply above to skills in the context of a business problem. Computer Science/IT Programming is an essential skill to become a data scientist but one needs not be a hard-core programmer to learn AI. Having familiarity with basic concepts of programming will ease the process of learning AI programming tools like Python/R. These basic concepts of programming should help a candidate get a long way on the journey to pursue a career in AI as it is all about writing efficient code to analyse big data and not being a master of programming. Individuals should learn the basics of programming in Python/R (or any relevant language) before they begin to work on AI problems/projects. Maths &amp;amp; Statistics AI teams have people from diverse backgrounds like chemical engineering, physics, economics, statistics, mathematics, operations research, computer science, etc. You will find many data scientists with a bachelor’s degree in statistics and machine learning but it is not a requirement to learn AI. However, having familiarity with the basic concepts of Math and Statistics like Linear Algebra, Calculus, Probability, etc. is important to learn AI. Domain/Business Knowledge Subsequently, the business knowledge that the data scientists would need to have would be related to the domain that the project/analysis is in. For instance, if the data scientist is working for a credit card department in a bank, it will need to understand the specific business definitions, regulations, accounting policies &amp;amp; international standards, processes etc. This is the part that is more specific to the organization the data scientist is deployed in. In my view, one thing to take care while the hiring data scientists is not to give huge preference to domain knowledge. This may severely limit the supply of AI talents to the organization. You would have a better chance of getting more value from AI by looking for those that are strong in math &amp;amp; programming, being able to convert business objectives to mathematical models. Based on my observation, this is a much more difficult skill to find or train, as compared to domain knowledge. Various Terminologies As an AI starter, you will come across many similar terminologies. First thing you need to do is to understand what each term means and where each fits in the bigger picture. Data Science, Business Intelligence, Data Mining, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Artificial Intelligence; let’s have a look at Wikipedia definition for each term &amp;amp; later see how these are interconnected. Data Science Data science is an interdisciplinary field that uses scientific methods, processes, algorithms and systems to extract knowledge and insights from data in various forms, both structured and unstructured, like data mining. Business Intelligence Business intelligence comprises the strategies and technologies used by enterprises for the data analysis of business information. BI technologies provide historical, current and predictive views of business operations. Data Mining Data mining is the process of discovering patterns in large data sets involving methods at the intersection of machine learning, statistics, and database systems. Machine Learning Machine learning is the scientific study of algorithms and statistical models that computer systems use to progressively improve their performance on a specific task. Deep Learning Deep learning is part of a broader family of machine learning methods based on learning data representations, as opposed to task-specific algorithms. Artificial Intelligence Artificial intelligence, sometimes called machine intelligence, is intelligence demonstrated by machines, in contrast to the natural intelligence displayed by humans and other animals. Interconnection Data mining uses statistics and other programming languages to find hidden patterns in the data to explain a certain phenomenon. It helps in building a perception about the data using both math and programming. Machine Learning deploys data mining techniques as well as other algorithms to develop models of what is happening behind some data to forecast future outcomes. Artificial Intelligence uses models developed by Machine Learning and other algorithms to lead to intelligent behaviour. AI is very much programming based. Data Mining demonstrates patterns Machine Learning forecasts with models Artificial Intelligence shapes behaviours So you see that these terms are different but still inter-connected. Roles in Artificial Intelligence Before looking into the skill-set of a data scientist, let’s have a look at various roles required to work and deliver a AI project, after all, it’s a teamwork. Every role has its own skills that are critical to AI projects at various stages. Data Scientist A data scientist is someone who knows how to extract meaning from and interpret data, which requires both tools and methods from statistics and machine learning. She spends a lot of time in the process of collecting, cleaning, and munging data. Domain knowledge is also an integral part of the skill. Machine Learning/AI Engineer Machine learning/AI engineers are sophisticated programmers who develop machines and systems that can learn and apply knowledge without specific domain requirement. Data Analyst Data analysts translate numbers into plain English. Every business collects data, whether it’s sales figures, market research, logistics, or transportation costs. A data analyst’s job is to take that data and use it to help companies make better business decisions. There are many different types of data analysts in the field, including operations analysts, marketing analysts, financial analysts, etc. Data Engineer Data Engineers are responsible for the creation and maintenance of analytics infrastructure that enables almost every other function in the data world. They are responsible for the development, construction, maintenance and testing of architectures, such as databases and large-scale processing systems. Data Architect Data architects build complex computer database systems for companies, either for the general public or for individual companies. They work with a team that looks at the needs of the database, the data that is available and creates a blueprint for creating, testing and maintaining that data architecture. Analytics Manager The analytics manager coordinates the different tasks that must be completed by their team for an AI project. Tasks may include researching and creating effective methods to collect data, analyzing information, and recommending solutions to business. Business Analyst AI business analyst converts the business problem statement to an AI problem statement which means what data needs to be analyzed to arrive at the insights. The data would then be reviewed with the technology team and results would be delivered to the business team in the form of insights and data patterns. The business analyst should also be knowledgeable enough to apply various predictive modelling techniques and right model selection for generating insights for the problem at hand. Quality Analyst The job of quality analyst includes checking the quality of the training data-set, preparing data-sets for testing, running statistics on human-labelled data-sets, evaluating precision and recall on the resulting ML model, reporting on unexpected patterns in outputs, and implementing necessary tools to automate repetitive parts of the work. Experience in software testing with data quality or DS/ML focus, understanding of statistics, exposure to AI / Machine Learning techniques and coding proficiency in Python, are some of the skills required for the job. To work on AI projects in any of the above mentioned roles, one needs to have an understanding of the core concepts at a high level but depth is required in the specific area you would be working in. Academia Vs Industry Academia and Industry are different fields with different people and culture. People working in Academia for longer tenure may find it difficult to adjust to industry culture and vice versa. There is also an academic trap when your career trajectory is so specialized for academia that you’re unprepared for a job outside of it. The academic trap happens in all areas of study, but for this post, we focus only on AI students who want to leave academia for AI positions. Further, companies are often hesitant to hire people coming straight from academia for various reasons like: In academia, individuals prefer writing papers over internships, making grants over learning programming languages, and not doing the things that could help you in the industry but not academia. The things that are important for academic hirings, such as papers, talks, and grants, are not as important in the industry. Working as a data scientist within a corporation requires an understanding of how the business world works, including how quickly deliverable need to be made, how to craft a good presentation, and how to word an email to make a request. In academia, you are encouraged to find the most innovative and elegant solution. In industry, you are encouraged to spend as little time as possible to find an analytical solution that just fits the need. Salary expectations for advanced degree holders are higher than someone with only an undergraduate degree. This also pushes away recruiters as the industry works in a different way, culture is simply different than the academic one. People coming from academia need to learn these lessons at their first job, which means that there is a lot of risk for the hiring company. Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI For Everyone Course Review &amp;amp; Key Takeaways</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/11/16/ai-for-everyone-course-review-key-takeaways.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI For Everyone Course Review &amp; Key Takeaways" /><published>2019-11-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-11-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/11/16/ai-for-everyone-course-review-key-takeaways</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/11/16/ai-for-everyone-course-review-key-takeaways.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/0*nvcqeUmzwF-AhSq4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy: &amp;lt;https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ankitrathi.com&quot;&gt;www.ankitrathi.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am working in ML/AI field for 6 years now and apart from technical skills that I acquired while working on the projects, I have also discussed various aspects of ML/AI with my non-technical colleagues, who have mostly been senior manager, VPs or CXOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I heard about “AI For Everyone” course, I was a bit reluctant in attending it as I thought I know most of the generic stuff that might have been talked in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, one of my colleagues discussed with me a few topics covered in this course which intrigued me to get a fresh perspective on these topics. So, I recently attended this course on Coursera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My motivation to write this blog is to make sure that I have understood key aspects of this course and am able to make my non-technical colleagues and project stakeholders understand the benefits &amp;amp; limitations of using AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog will also serve as a refresher for the professionals who have already attended it or are working in AI field but couldn’t attend the course due to time limitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review-of-thecourse&quot;&gt;Review of the Course&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“AI For Everyone” is a short non-technical course which helps to bridge the gap among corporate professionals who are going to be impacted by AI transformation now or in the near future. Even the professionals without programming background understand the capabilities and limitations of today’s AI, what it takes to incorporate AI into your company’s strategy, how some of the fear regarding AI is overhyped and finally many serious questions like how AI will impact repetitive automation-prone jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key aspects of this course are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A non-technical overview of AI field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mainly for non-technical staff including executives (VPs &amp;amp; CXOs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refresher for AI starters &amp;amp; enthusiasts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brings all stakeholders for AI projects on the same page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mostly covers benefits &amp;amp; limitations of AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, the most important benefit of this course is that it brings all the professionals on the same page about what is AI? What are its capabilities? Which really fills a lot of gaps for the people joining AI projects from different background and reduces the friction while working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;outline-of-thecourse&quot;&gt;Outline of the Course&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at what we are going to learn in this course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First week: AI technology, what is AI and what is machine learning? What’s supervised learning, that is learning inputs, outputs, or A to B mappings. As well as what is data science, and how data feeds into all of these technologies? What AI can and cannot do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second week: What it feels like to build an AI project? What is the workflow of machine learning projects, of collecting data, building a system and deploying it, as well as the workflow of data science projects? How to carry out technical diligence to make sure a project is feasible, together with business diligence to make sure that the project is valuable before you commit to taking on a specific AI project?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third week: How such AI projects could fit in the context of our company? Examples of complex AI products, such as a smart speaker, a self-driving car. What are the roles and responsibilities of large AI teams? The AI transmission playbook, what are the five-steps for helping a company become a great AI company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last week: AI and Society. What are the limitations of AI beyond just technical ones? How AI is affecting developing economies and jobs worldwide?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;week-1-what-isai&quot;&gt;Week 1: What is AI?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*gkfny80zfEf6KHYmvQYN2w.png&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy: &amp;lt;https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s content contains all the essentials for understanding AI, its capabilities, limitations, and how to implement it in a company’s automated processes to become an AI company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI is creating value in almost all the sectors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artificial Intelligence can be categorized broadly into two streams: ANI &amp;amp; AGI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artificial General Intelligence (AGI): Machine can do whatever a human can do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artificial Narrow Intelligence (ANI): Machine can do very specific tasks like driving cars, playing asked music, searching web etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What we know how to develop today are ANIs, each specialized in one task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AGI doesn’t exist yet (at least for a long time from now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI has really taken off recently due to the rise of neural networks and deep learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the majority of the cases: AI → Machine Learning → Supervised Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supervised Learning learns the mapping between input A to output B&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-isdata&quot;&gt;What is data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We know that Supervised Learning learns the mapping between input A to output B&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples of input A &amp;amp; output B from which ML algorithms learn is called data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data is often unique to your business, can be structured (tables, hierarchy etc), unstructured ( text, voice and image) or semi-structured&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data can be obtained by: manual labeling, observing behaviours or download from websites/partnerships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pre-process the data before using it for AI models: garbage in, garbage out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the data problems are related to incorrect labels &amp;amp; missing values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-terminology-ofai&quot;&gt;The terminology of AI&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business Intelligence (BI) helps interpret past data, BI is mainly used for reporting or Descriptive Analytics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Science is the science of extracting knowledge and insights from data which often ends up being captured in a deck.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine Learning is the field of study that gives computers the ability to learn without being explicitly programmed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Machine Learning which is a subset of the AI ​​itself contains subsets of which the most powerful is the Deep Learning (DL&lt;strong&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Originally inspired by neural networks of the brain, DL models are composed of several layers of computational units (artificial neurons), each capable of detecting more and more complicated characteristics of a training dataset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-makes-an-aicompany&quot;&gt;What makes an AI company?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any company + deep learning != AI company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategic data acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unified data warehouse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pervasive automation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New roles &amp;amp; division of labour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-steps-to-becoming-an-aicompany&quot;&gt;5 steps to becoming an AI company&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Execute pilot projects to gain momentum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build an in-house AI team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide broad AI training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop an AI strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop internal &amp;amp; external communications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-machine-learning-can-and-cannotdo&quot;&gt;What Machine Learning can and cannot do&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ML/AI can’t do everything&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectations are inflated due to media, academics &amp;amp; only positive reports about AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imperfect rule: Whatever we could do with a second of thought can probably be automated using AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical diligence is required to assess the feasibility of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is still harder to contextualize the responses for AI models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ML tends to work well in learning a simple concept with lots of available data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ML tends to work poorly in learning a complex concept, especially from small amount of data or if performing on new type of data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;intuitive-explanation-of-deeplearning&quot;&gt;Intuitive explanation of deep learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;week-2-building-aiprojects&quot;&gt;Week 2: Building AI Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*FgHHmzBXNJsYWypLJWCN6w.png&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy: &amp;lt;https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content of this week contains all the essentials for developing an AI project (large or small) and understanding how all jobs will be impacted by AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;workflow-of-a-machine-learningproject&quot;&gt;Workflow of a Machine Learning project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collect data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train model (iterate until its good enough)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploy model (get data back, maintain/update model)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;workflow-of-a-data-scienceproject&quot;&gt;Workflow of a Data Science project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collect data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyse data (iterate until its good enough)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suggest hypotheses/actions (deploy changes, re-analyse periodically)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;every-job-function-needs-to-learn-to-usedata&quot;&gt;Every job function needs to learn to use data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing sales: optimizing sales funnel &amp;amp; automated lead sorting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Default detection: optimizing manufacturing line &amp;amp; automated visual inspection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recruitment assistance: optimizing recruitment funnel &amp;amp; automated resume screening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product recommendation: A/B testing &amp;amp; customized product recommendation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Precision agriculture: crop analytics &amp;amp; precise weed killing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-choose-an-aiproject&quot;&gt;How to choose an AI project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organize a cross-functional brainstorming with both the AI and domain teams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cross-section between ‘What AI can do’ &amp;amp; ‘What is valuable for your business’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which either increase revenue or reduce costs or both&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use/buy standard AI models and develop only which don’t exist or offer extra business value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;method-i&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automation of processes/tasks rather than jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selection of activities with the greatest impact on the company’s business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selection of the main pain points in the company’s business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;method-ii&quot;&gt;Method II&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical diligence in terms of state of the art AI capability, data requirements &amp;amp; time and people required to create, train &amp;amp; deploy AI models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business diligence in terms of cost reduction, revenue increment &amp;amp; new product/business opportunity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethical considerations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;working-with-an-aiteam&quot;&gt;Working with an AI team&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead of hiring AI specialist, train IT engineers in AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domain team must define the performance rate to be achieved by the AI ​​model&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not realistic to ask the AI ​​team to obtain a 100% performance rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Due to limitations of ML, insufficient data, mislabelled data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technical-tools-for-aiteams&quot;&gt;Technical tools for AI teams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI ​​evolves largely in the Open Source world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free ML/DL high-quality frameworks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Academic research papers in ML/DL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refer Arxiv for research publications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refer GitHub for Open Source repositories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI ​​team must also have the significant computational capacity (GPU)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be local or by prominent cloud providers (AWS, Azure &amp;amp; GCP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;big-data-is-not-alwaysrequired&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data is not always required&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having more data almost never hurts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data makes some businesses defensible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But with small data, you can still make progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;week-3-building-ai-in-yourcompany&quot;&gt;Week 3: Building AI in your Company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*8giUXsK_AECrx54NUbHt6A.png&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy: &amp;lt;https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s content contains all the essential elements for developing AI in an organization (association, public organization, company).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;case-study-smartspeaker&quot;&gt;Case study: Smart speaker&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Typical examples: Amazon Echo/Alexa, Google Home, Apple Siri, Baidu DuerOS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steps to process the voice command:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Trigger word/wakeword detection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Speech recognition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Intent recognition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Execute task&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually, there is one AI team per process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Execution of the task may be more complex to be broken down in further sub-tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example tasks: play music, volume up/down, make call, current time etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;case-study-self-driving-car&quot;&gt;Case study: Self-driving car&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are 3 main steps for a self-driving car to decide on its route and speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But there are many other localization processes that are necessary for the decision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key steps: Car detection → Pedestrian detection → Motion planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;example-roles-of-an-aiteam&quot;&gt;Example roles of an AI team&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;: 50% or more of the team, in charge of developing software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ML Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;: responsible for creating and training ML models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ML Researcher&lt;/strong&gt;: in charge of following the evolution of state-of-the-art, doing research and possibly publishing the results of its research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applied ML Scientist&lt;/strong&gt;: in charge of adapting already published models to the specific projects of its company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Scientist:&lt;/strong&gt; responsible for examining the data and providing the insights to AI team/executives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; in charge of organizing and saving data in an accessible, secure and cost-effective way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Product Manager:&lt;/strong&gt; help AI team in deciding what to build, what’s feasible &amp;amp; valuable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with a small team and expand based on the progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ai-transformation-playbook&quot;&gt;AI Transformation Playbook&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Execute pilot projects to gain momentum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build an in-house AI team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide broad AI training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop an AI strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop internal &amp;amp; external communications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ai-pitfalls-toavoid&quot;&gt;AI pitfalls to avoid&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t expect AI to solve each and everything&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t depend solely on the technical team to come up with AI use-cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t expect the AI project to work the first time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t expect traditional planning &amp;amp; processes to apply without any changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t think you need superstar AI engineer to succeed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;taking-your-first-step-inai&quot;&gt;Taking your first step in AI&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get colleagues to learn about AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start brainstorming about projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire a few ML/AI people to help&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire or appoint an AI leader&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discuss with CXOs/Board about possibilities of AI transformations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;survey-of-major-ai-applications&quot;&gt;Survey of major AI applications&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer Vision: Image classification, Object recognition, Object detection, Image segmentation, Tracking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing: Text classification, Information retrieval, Name entity recognition, Machine translation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speech: Speech recognition, Trigger word/wakeword detection, Speaker ID, Speech synthesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robotics: Perception, Motion planning, Control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General Machine Learning: Unstructured data (image, audio, text), Structured data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;survey-of-major-ai-techniques&quot;&gt;Survey of major AI techniques&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsupervised learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transfer learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generative Adversarial Network (GANs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge Graph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;week-4-ai-andsociety&quot;&gt;Week 4: AI and Society&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*XIsCsSMya6ahjOyLwI1TSQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy: &amp;lt;https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s content contains all the essentials to understand the impacts of AI on our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-realistic-view-ofai&quot;&gt;A realistic view of AI&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too optimistic: Sentient/super-intelligent AI killer robots coming soon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too pessimistic: AI cannot do everything, so an AI winter is coming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just right: AI can’t do each and everything, but will transform industries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance limitations: with unavailability of data, less or irrelevant data or randomness of patterns can limit the performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model explainability: explainable models are more accepted in business &amp;amp; society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discrimination-bias&quot;&gt;Discrimination / Bias&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI model may develop gender and ethnic biases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem comes from the training data which contain these biases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples such as:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Hiring tool discriminating against women&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Facial recognition working better for light-skinned individuals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Bank loan approvals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Toxic effect of reinforcing unhealthy stereotypes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combating bias:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Technical solutions: removing bias in training data, using more inclusive data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Transparency and/or auditing processes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Having a diverse workforce&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adversarial-attacks&quot;&gt;Adversarial attacks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AL models are sensitive to adversarial attacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which are deliberate actions to fool an AI model&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is possible by changing the values ​​of a few pixels of an image to fool a classifier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While visually we (humans) can not detect the changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adversarial defence do exist, but incur some cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endless race between forgers and authorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adverse-uses&quot;&gt;Adverse uses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DeepFakes: Synthesize video of people doing things they never did&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Undermining of democracy &amp;amp; privacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generating fake comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ai-and-developing-nations&quot;&gt;AI and developing nations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing economies can ‘leapfrog’ by using technology developed by others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like mobile phones, mobile payments, online education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use applied AI in specific industries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public-private partnerships to accelerate development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invent in AI education of citizen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ai-andjobs&quot;&gt;AI and jobs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automation of activities by AI already has an impact on employment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But job created by AI should be much higher than job displaced by 2030&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should assess what are the tasks in our day-to-day job which can be automated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Possibility of conditional basic income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a lifelong learning society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Political solutions to support AI transformation in society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should all complement our current knowledge with an AI knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s recap what we have learnt in this course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First week: AI technology, what is AI and what is machine learning? What’s supervised learning, that is learning inputs, outputs, or A to B mappings. As well as what is data science, and how data feeds into all of these technologies? What AI can and cannot do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second week: What it feels like to build an AI project? What is the workflow of machine learning projects, of collecting data, building a system and deploying it, as well as the workflow of data science projects? How to carry out technical diligence to make sure a project is feasible, together with business diligence to make sure that the project is valuable before you commit to taking on a specific AI project?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third week: How such AI projects could fit in the context of our company? Examples of complex AI products, such as a smart speaker, a self-driving car. What are the roles and responsibilities of large AI teams? The AI transmission playbook, what are the five-steps for helping a company become a great AI company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last week: AI and Society. What are the limitations of AI beyond just technical ones? How AI is affecting developing economies and jobs worldwide?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have learned a lot in these four weeks, but AI is a complex topic, so the key is to keep learning, keep evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed]&lt;br /&gt;
[embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Want to learn more? visit www.ankitrathi.com I am working in ML/AI field for 6 years now and apart from technical skills that I acquired while working on the projects, I have also discussed various aspects of ML/AI with my non-technical colleagues, who have mostly been senior manager, VPs or CXOs. When I heard about “AI For Everyone” course, I was a bit reluctant in attending it as I thought I know most of the generic stuff that might have been talked in the course. Recently, one of my colleagues discussed with me a few topics covered in this course which intrigued me to get a fresh perspective on these topics. So, I recently attended this course on Coursera. My motivation to write this blog is to make sure that I have understood key aspects of this course and am able to make my non-technical colleagues and project stakeholders understand the benefits &amp;amp; limitations of using AI. This blog will also serve as a refresher for the professionals who have already attended it or are working in AI field but couldn’t attend the course due to time limitation. Review of the Course “AI For Everyone” is a short non-technical course which helps to bridge the gap among corporate professionals who are going to be impacted by AI transformation now or in the near future. Even the professionals without programming background understand the capabilities and limitations of today’s AI, what it takes to incorporate AI into your company’s strategy, how some of the fear regarding AI is overhyped and finally many serious questions like how AI will impact repetitive automation-prone jobs. Key aspects of this course are: A non-technical overview of AI field Mainly for non-technical staff including executives (VPs &amp;amp; CXOs) Refresher for AI starters &amp;amp; enthusiasts Brings all stakeholders for AI projects on the same page Mostly covers benefits &amp;amp; limitations of AI In my view, the most important benefit of this course is that it brings all the professionals on the same page about what is AI? What are its capabilities? Which really fills a lot of gaps for the people joining AI projects from different background and reduces the friction while working together. Outline of the Course Let’s have a look at what we are going to learn in this course: First week: AI technology, what is AI and what is machine learning? What’s supervised learning, that is learning inputs, outputs, or A to B mappings. As well as what is data science, and how data feeds into all of these technologies? What AI can and cannot do? Second week: What it feels like to build an AI project? What is the workflow of machine learning projects, of collecting data, building a system and deploying it, as well as the workflow of data science projects? How to carry out technical diligence to make sure a project is feasible, together with business diligence to make sure that the project is valuable before you commit to taking on a specific AI project? Third week: How such AI projects could fit in the context of our company? Examples of complex AI products, such as a smart speaker, a self-driving car. What are the roles and responsibilities of large AI teams? The AI transmission playbook, what are the five-steps for helping a company become a great AI company? Last week: AI and Society. What are the limitations of AI beyond just technical ones? How AI is affecting developing economies and jobs worldwide? Week 1: What is AI? This week’s content contains all the essentials for understanding AI, its capabilities, limitations, and how to implement it in a company’s automated processes to become an AI company. Introduction AI is creating value in almost all the sectors Artificial Intelligence can be categorized broadly into two streams: ANI &amp;amp; AGI Artificial General Intelligence (AGI): Machine can do whatever a human can do Artificial Narrow Intelligence (ANI): Machine can do very specific tasks like driving cars, playing asked music, searching web etc What we know how to develop today are ANIs, each specialized in one task AGI doesn’t exist yet (at least for a long time from now) Machine Learning AI has really taken off recently due to the rise of neural networks and deep learning In the majority of the cases: AI → Machine Learning → Supervised Learning Supervised Learning learns the mapping between input A to output B What is data We know that Supervised Learning learns the mapping between input A to output B Examples of input A &amp;amp; output B from which ML algorithms learn is called data Data is often unique to your business, can be structured (tables, hierarchy etc), unstructured ( text, voice and image) or semi-structured Data can be obtained by: manual labeling, observing behaviours or download from websites/partnerships Pre-process the data before using it for AI models: garbage in, garbage out Most of the data problems are related to incorrect labels &amp;amp; missing values The terminology of AI Business Intelligence (BI) helps interpret past data, BI is mainly used for reporting or Descriptive Analytics. Data Science is the science of extracting knowledge and insights from data which often ends up being captured in a deck. Machine Learning is the field of study that gives computers the ability to learn without being explicitly programmed. The Machine Learning which is a subset of the AI ​​itself contains subsets of which the most powerful is the Deep Learning (DL). Originally inspired by neural networks of the brain, DL models are composed of several layers of computational units (artificial neurons), each capable of detecting more and more complicated characteristics of a training dataset What makes an AI company? Any company + deep learning != AI company Strategic data acquisition Unified data warehouse Pervasive automation New roles &amp;amp; division of labour 5 steps to becoming an AI company Execute pilot projects to gain momentum Build an in-house AI team Provide broad AI training Develop an AI strategy Develop internal &amp;amp; external communications What Machine Learning can and cannot do ML/AI can’t do everything Expectations are inflated due to media, academics &amp;amp; only positive reports about AI Imperfect rule: Whatever we could do with a second of thought can probably be automated using AI Technical diligence is required to assess the feasibility of the project It is still harder to contextualize the responses for AI models ML tends to work well in learning a simple concept with lots of available data ML tends to work poorly in learning a complex concept, especially from small amount of data or if performing on new type of data Intuitive explanation of deep learning Week 2: Building AI Projects The content of this week contains all the essentials for developing an AI project (large or small) and understanding how all jobs will be impacted by AI. Workflow of a Machine Learning project Collect data Train model (iterate until its good enough) Deploy model (get data back, maintain/update model) Workflow of a Data Science project Collect data Analyse data (iterate until its good enough) Suggest hypotheses/actions (deploy changes, re-analyse periodically) Every job function needs to learn to use data Increasing sales: optimizing sales funnel &amp;amp; automated lead sorting Default detection: optimizing manufacturing line &amp;amp; automated visual inspection Recruitment assistance: optimizing recruitment funnel &amp;amp; automated resume screening Product recommendation: A/B testing &amp;amp; customized product recommendation Precision agriculture: crop analytics &amp;amp; precise weed killing How to choose an AI project organize a cross-functional brainstorming with both the AI and domain teams Cross-section between ‘What AI can do’ &amp;amp; ‘What is valuable for your business’ Which either increase revenue or reduce costs or both Use/buy standard AI models and develop only which don’t exist or offer extra business value Method I Automation of processes/tasks rather than jobs Selection of activities with the greatest impact on the company’s business Selection of the main pain points in the company’s business Method II Technical diligence in terms of state of the art AI capability, data requirements &amp;amp; time and people required to create, train &amp;amp; deploy AI models Business diligence in terms of cost reduction, revenue increment &amp;amp; new product/business opportunity Ethical considerations Working with an AI team Instead of hiring AI specialist, train IT engineers in AI Domain team must define the performance rate to be achieved by the AI ​​model Not realistic to ask the AI ​​team to obtain a 100% performance rate Due to limitations of ML, insufficient data, mislabelled data Technical tools for AI teams AI ​​evolves largely in the Open Source world Free ML/DL high-quality frameworks Academic research papers in ML/DL Refer Arxiv for research publications Refer GitHub for Open Source repositories AI ​​team must also have the significant computational capacity (GPU) Can be local or by prominent cloud providers (AWS, Azure &amp;amp; GCP) Big data is not always required Having more data almost never hurts Data makes some businesses defensible But with small data, you can still make progress Week 3: Building AI in your Company This week’s content contains all the essential elements for developing AI in an organization (association, public organization, company). Case study: Smart speaker Typical examples: Amazon Echo/Alexa, Google Home, Apple Siri, Baidu DuerOS Steps to process the voice command: — Trigger word/wakeword detection — Speech recognition — Intent recognition — Execute task Usually, there is one AI team per process Execution of the task may be more complex to be broken down in further sub-tasks Example tasks: play music, volume up/down, make call, current time etc Case study: Self-driving car There are 3 main steps for a self-driving car to decide on its route and speed But there are many other localization processes that are necessary for the decision Key steps: Car detection → Pedestrian detection → Motion planning Example roles of an AI team Software Engineer: 50% or more of the team, in charge of developing software ML Engineer: responsible for creating and training ML models ML Researcher: in charge of following the evolution of state-of-the-art, doing research and possibly publishing the results of its research Applied ML Scientist: in charge of adapting already published models to the specific projects of its company. Data Scientist: responsible for examining the data and providing the insights to AI team/executives Data Engineer: in charge of organizing and saving data in an accessible, secure and cost-effective way AI Product Manager: help AI team in deciding what to build, what’s feasible &amp;amp; valuable Start with a small team and expand based on the progress AI Transformation Playbook Execute pilot projects to gain momentum Build an in-house AI team Provide broad AI training Develop an AI strategy Develop internal &amp;amp; external communications AI pitfalls to avoid Don’t expect AI to solve each and everything Don’t depend solely on the technical team to come up with AI use-cases Don’t expect the AI project to work the first time Don’t expect traditional planning &amp;amp; processes to apply without any changes Don’t think you need superstar AI engineer to succeed Taking your first step in AI Get colleagues to learn about AI Start brainstorming about projects Hire a few ML/AI people to help Hire or appoint an AI leader Discuss with CXOs/Board about possibilities of AI transformations Survey of major AI applications Computer Vision: Image classification, Object recognition, Object detection, Image segmentation, Tracking Natural Language Processing: Text classification, Information retrieval, Name entity recognition, Machine translation Speech: Speech recognition, Trigger word/wakeword detection, Speaker ID, Speech synthesis Robotics: Perception, Motion planning, Control General Machine Learning: Unstructured data (image, audio, text), Structured data Survey of major AI techniques Unsupervised learning Transfer learning Reinforcement learning Generative Adversarial Network (GANs) Knowledge Graph Week 4: AI and Society This week’s content contains all the essentials to understand the impacts of AI on our society. A realistic view of AI Too optimistic: Sentient/super-intelligent AI killer robots coming soon Too pessimistic: AI cannot do everything, so an AI winter is coming Just right: AI can’t do each and everything, but will transform industries Performance limitations: with unavailability of data, less or irrelevant data or randomness of patterns can limit the performance Model explainability: explainable models are more accepted in business &amp;amp; society Discrimination / Bias AI model may develop gender and ethnic biases Problem comes from the training data which contain these biases Examples such as: — Hiring tool discriminating against women — Facial recognition working better for light-skinned individuals — Bank loan approvals — Toxic effect of reinforcing unhealthy stereotypes Combating bias: — Technical solutions: removing bias in training data, using more inclusive data — Transparency and/or auditing processes — Having a diverse workforce Adversarial attacks AL models are sensitive to adversarial attacks Which are deliberate actions to fool an AI model It is possible by changing the values ​​of a few pixels of an image to fool a classifier While visually we (humans) can not detect the changes Adversarial defence do exist, but incur some cost Endless race between forgers and authorities Adverse uses DeepFakes: Synthesize video of people doing things they never did Undermining of democracy &amp;amp; privacy Generating fake comments AI and developing nations Developing economies can ‘leapfrog’ by using technology developed by others Like mobile phones, mobile payments, online education Use applied AI in specific industries Public-private partnerships to accelerate development Invent in AI education of citizen AI and jobs Automation of activities by AI already has an impact on employment But job created by AI should be much higher than job displaced by 2030 We should assess what are the tasks in our day-to-day job which can be automated Possibility of conditional basic income Building a lifelong learning society Political solutions to support AI transformation in society We should all complement our current knowledge with an AI knowledge Conclusion Let’s recap what we have learnt in this course: First week: AI technology, what is AI and what is machine learning? What’s supervised learning, that is learning inputs, outputs, or A to B mappings. As well as what is data science, and how data feeds into all of these technologies? What AI can and cannot do? Second week: What it feels like to build an AI project? What is the workflow of machine learning projects, of collecting data, building a system and deploying it, as well as the workflow of data science projects? How to carry out technical diligence to make sure a project is feasible, together with business diligence to make sure that the project is valuable before you commit to taking on a specific AI project? Third week: How such AI projects could fit in the context of our company? Examples of complex AI products, such as a smart speaker, a self-driving car. What are the roles and responsibilities of large AI teams? The AI transmission playbook, what are the five-steps for helping a company become a great AI company? Last week: AI and Society. What are the limitations of AI beyond just technical ones? How AI is affecting developing economies and jobs worldwide? We have learned a lot in these four weeks, but AI is a complex topic, so the key is to keep learning, keep evolving. References [embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed] [embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed] If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’ [embed]https://www.deeplearning.ai/ai-for-everyone/[/embed] Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to build your career in Artificial Intelligence?</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/10/05/how-to-build-your-career-in-artificial-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to build your career in Artificial Intelligence?" /><published>2019-10-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-10-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/10/05/how-to-build-your-career-in-artificial-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/10/05/how-to-build-your-career-in-artificial-intelligence.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*2R90ZlbJ7KTH_92WX1PWMw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;ankitrathi.com&lt;/a&gt; now to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— to read my blog posts on various topics of AI/ML&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— to keep a tab on latest &amp;amp; relevant news/articles daily from AI/ML world&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— to refer free &amp;amp; useful AI/ML resources&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— to buy my books on discounted price&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— to know more about me and what I am up to these days&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start learning a new skill, the first thing is to look at the big picture and where your would-be skills fit in the field. It gives you a context of what role you can play or are expected to play. And when the skill and field are evolving &amp;amp; overwhelmingly large, you are so engrossed in the details that most probably you tend to miss the purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*QaxMn8xlcddwkvqi&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, to understand the big picture, ask yourself ‘why’ more often and start with the end in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following analogy is not particularly about artificial intelligence but in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ouBVb36WCi7rX-d0fPAyCA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see above, to land the job you want you to need to crack the interview. To get the call for the interview, you need a network that can refer you for opportunities. To have a relevant &amp;amp; helpful network, you need to have impressive credentials or portfolio. To have a solid portfolio, you need to work on the core skills of the job role that you want. To build core skills, you need to have the right resources. To gather the right resources, you need to have awareness of the field in which you want to build your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*C85AlKxUNOXhg5t6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, reverse the order and assess at what stage you are and fill the gap in the coming months to build your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the above approach, this post gives you a holistic view of what you need to know and do to build your road-map in the artificial intelligence field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*WbImY9K7LGeWVuwb.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us see what you would be doing in each of the steps in the above framework to build your career in artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;navigate-the-landscape&quot;&gt;Navigate the landscape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before learning artificial intelligence, it is very much required that you understand the overall landscape and where all the buzzwords like artificial intelligence, machine learning, deep learning fit in. In this step, you need to learn different terminologies, their meaning and how these are interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*2qBWJu4k4DzJPDtg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is a vast field, not a single person has all the required knowledge or does all day to day tasks. Due to the variety of skills required in artificial intelligence projects, specific roles are evolving so that individual can contribute according to their abilities. As part of this step, you also need to know almost all the artificial intelligence roles, which will give you a better idea which one suits you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;work-on-buildingblocks&quot;&gt;Work on building blocks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the core part of artificial intelligence, knowing the concept, process &amp;amp; tools are the most important part of any job. In this step, you need to be aware of what is in the scope of the artificial intelligence field and which role need to have what kind of skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*1pF2NecfM710TOhU&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing this step you should know what is in the scope of the artificial intelligence field. You can relate the concepts, process &amp;amp; tools based on the role you think you can fit in. Think of this step as defining the scope of the artificial intelligence field with electives based on your role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;utilize-the-resources&quot;&gt;Utilize the resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no dearth of learning resources but that has only confused the starters in the artificial intelligence field. I get many questions related to what books to read, what courses to enrol, what blogs/portals to follow, what data-sets to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*J-gdyoHb7cpG1CWm&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this step, you need to make a list of all the prominent books, courses, blogs, portals, data-sets &amp;amp; podcasts etc. Please note that this list should be as you get more exposure to the field, there may be additional and better resources but I think you will get enough exposure after going through this step to evaluate other resources comparatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;build-your-portfolio&quot;&gt;Build your portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refining &amp;amp; honing the skills required for a job is one part, showcasing what you can offer is another. What if you have all the required skills but nobody looking for the skill-set is aware that you do. Having a credible portfolio is an effective way to showcase your skill-set and talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*UNlAoO0XDZSYjqE_&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this step, you should know what is needed to build an impressive portfolio even before entering the market looking for a relevant job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;network--land-thejob&quot;&gt;Network &amp;amp; land the job&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, you have filtered the best-suited role &amp;amp; honed your skill-set &amp;amp; built the portfolio as well. Your mission is not accomplished unless you have like-minded professionals in your network who are aware of your capabilities and can refer you for the jobs that match your skills. Interview preparation is another task in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*xXI2-TjXfoCNb2AG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this step, you will focus on the steps required to network &amp;amp; land the job in the artificial intelligence field. How to network with like-minded professionals, how to search for relevant job openings, how to prepare &amp;amp; crack artificial intelligence interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-your-career-future-proof&quot;&gt;Make your career future-proof&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future-proofing your career is simply taking the extra steps to prepare yourself for constant technology disruption, one that’s going to rely heavily on adaptability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*pvNnfA6WFa2bX9Fs.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So rather than waiting for someone or technology to replace your labour, you need to take a proactive approach to put yourself in a position where potential employers can’t afford to work with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is an evolving field due to ongoing technology disruption. While the core concepts remain the same; tools, technology &amp;amp; frameworks will be changing. Any roadmap prepared for artificial intelligence has to be reviewed at a regular interval, so keep a tab on what’s happening in the artificial intelligence field and revise your roadmap accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[embed]https://medium.com/\@rathi.ankit/how-to-launch-your-ds-ai-career-in-12-weeks-8a7e6950ffe6[/embed]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Visit ankitrathi.com now to: — to read my blog posts on various topics of AI/ML — to keep a tab on latest &amp;amp; relevant news/articles daily from AI/ML world — to refer free &amp;amp; useful AI/ML resources — to buy my books on discounted price — to know more about me and what I am up to these days When you start learning a new skill, the first thing is to look at the big picture and where your would-be skills fit in the field. It gives you a context of what role you can play or are expected to play. And when the skill and field are evolving &amp;amp; overwhelmingly large, you are so engrossed in the details that most probably you tend to miss the purpose. In my view, to understand the big picture, ask yourself ‘why’ more often and start with the end in your mind. The following analogy is not particularly about artificial intelligence but in general. As you can see above, to land the job you want you to need to crack the interview. To get the call for the interview, you need a network that can refer you for opportunities. To have a relevant &amp;amp; helpful network, you need to have impressive credentials or portfolio. To have a solid portfolio, you need to work on the core skills of the job role that you want. To build core skills, you need to have the right resources. To gather the right resources, you need to have awareness of the field in which you want to build your career. Now, reverse the order and assess at what stage you are and fill the gap in the coming months to build your career. Based on the above approach, this post gives you a holistic view of what you need to know and do to build your road-map in the artificial intelligence field. Now let us see what you would be doing in each of the steps in the above framework to build your career in artificial intelligence. Navigate the landscape Before learning artificial intelligence, it is very much required that you understand the overall landscape and where all the buzzwords like artificial intelligence, machine learning, deep learning fit in. In this step, you need to learn different terminologies, their meaning and how these are interconnected. Artificial intelligence is a vast field, not a single person has all the required knowledge or does all day to day tasks. Due to the variety of skills required in artificial intelligence projects, specific roles are evolving so that individual can contribute according to their abilities. As part of this step, you also need to know almost all the artificial intelligence roles, which will give you a better idea which one suits you. Work on building blocks This is the core part of artificial intelligence, knowing the concept, process &amp;amp; tools are the most important part of any job. In this step, you need to be aware of what is in the scope of the artificial intelligence field and which role need to have what kind of skills. After completing this step you should know what is in the scope of the artificial intelligence field. You can relate the concepts, process &amp;amp; tools based on the role you think you can fit in. Think of this step as defining the scope of the artificial intelligence field with electives based on your role. Utilize the resources There is no dearth of learning resources but that has only confused the starters in the artificial intelligence field. I get many questions related to what books to read, what courses to enrol, what blogs/portals to follow, what data-sets to work on. As part of this step, you need to make a list of all the prominent books, courses, blogs, portals, data-sets &amp;amp; podcasts etc. Please note that this list should be as you get more exposure to the field, there may be additional and better resources but I think you will get enough exposure after going through this step to evaluate other resources comparatively. Build your portfolio Refining &amp;amp; honing the skills required for a job is one part, showcasing what you can offer is another. What if you have all the required skills but nobody looking for the skill-set is aware that you do. Having a credible portfolio is an effective way to showcase your skill-set and talent. In this step, you should know what is needed to build an impressive portfolio even before entering the market looking for a relevant job. Network &amp;amp; land the job You know, you have filtered the best-suited role &amp;amp; honed your skill-set &amp;amp; built the portfolio as well. Your mission is not accomplished unless you have like-minded professionals in your network who are aware of your capabilities and can refer you for the jobs that match your skills. Interview preparation is another task in itself. As part of this step, you will focus on the steps required to network &amp;amp; land the job in the artificial intelligence field. How to network with like-minded professionals, how to search for relevant job openings, how to prepare &amp;amp; crack artificial intelligence interviews. Make your career future-proof Future-proofing your career is simply taking the extra steps to prepare yourself for constant technology disruption, one that’s going to rely heavily on adaptability. So rather than waiting for someone or technology to replace your labour, you need to take a proactive approach to put yourself in a position where potential employers can’t afford to work with you. Conclusion Artificial intelligence is an evolving field due to ongoing technology disruption. While the core concepts remain the same; tools, technology &amp;amp; frameworks will be changing. Any roadmap prepared for artificial intelligence has to be reviewed at a regular interval, so keep a tab on what’s happening in the artificial intelligence field and revise your roadmap accordingly. If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’ [embed]https://medium.com/\@rathi.ankit/how-to-launch-your-ds-ai-career-in-12-weeks-8a7e6950ffe6[/embed] Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Intelligence for Business Leaders</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/09/05/artificial-intelligence-for-business-leaders.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Intelligence for Business Leaders" /><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/09/05/artificial-intelligence-for-business-leaders</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/09/05/artificial-intelligence-for-business-leaders.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*J8upfmjxMdQDCppmtfZnCg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Jehyun Sung](https://unsplash.com/@jaysung?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/search/photos/leaders?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that data is the new oil and AI is the new electricity. Due to the difference AI can make in every walk of life, it is the red hot subject among recent graduates/undergraduates and working professionals in different industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only up to the technical team to make AI initiatives a success in the organization. Business value creation in driven top-down so business leaders is equally responsible for the success or failure of AI initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the failure rate of AI projects and the challenges faced by AI teams, you can easily figure out that most of the challenges are because of the absence of data culture in an organization. And data culture can’t be inculcated in a day, it takes efforts and leadership needs to drive it as part of their change management program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from infusing data culture in the organization, most of the decisions in business are made by its leaders, AI is providing huge opportunity to many areas of business across domains. Hence as a leader or manager, understanding AI and applying it effectively in our organization can make all the difference between us and our competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I published a book for AI starters and enthusiasts, where I shared a learning framework on how they can get into AI and during my discussions with managers and business leaders, they asked me if a similar framework can be built for business leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;framework&quot;&gt;Framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the day to day working of managers and leaders, they need not know each and everything of the work &amp;amp; resources they are managing but just enough awareness can make a huge impact on AI initiatives. It helps in setting the right expectations with the customer or business, defining better strategy, anticipating challenges and understanding the concerns of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is the framework that I came up with for business leaders &amp;amp; managers: Prepare, Strategize, Execute, Reflect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*aY5a9cKjsXfgBOXWk5VcWQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us have a look at each of the phase of the above framework:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt;Prepare&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*cwPtydKOq61YUHq_&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is a new &amp;amp; evolving field, the first phase for us is to prepare ourselves to run these AI initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first step we need to take is to navigate the overall landscape. What are AI, ML, DL, DS, DM, BI terms? How they are interconnected? What is the typical lifecycle to execute AI project? What are the different roles and skill-set required in the lifecycle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step would be to build the capability to execute AI projects. More we work on our concepts and skill-set, more we will be comfortable to run such projects and handling teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strategize&quot;&gt;Strategize&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*JtXoL69kR3KjXikI&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working on our concepts &amp;amp; skill-set, we are ready to work with a team on AI projects but hold on. How do we know what are the opportunities in our organization? Working on which projects would be more beneficial than others? To get answers to these questions, we need to define an AI strategy based on our organization &amp;amp; industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from defining the strategy, we need to have an operational framework in place to get a clear understanding of what is to be done and who will be doing what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area for leaders/manager is to anticipate what challenges their teams would face while working on AI projects. Having a view beforehand will help you to handle the challenges better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;execute&quot;&gt;Execute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*rIqg9-0ptv3mhlw7&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phase covers managing the on-field execution of AI projects. As AI projects are different from typical IT projects, we need to emphasize quick POC to get a better view of the problem &amp;amp; to provide optimized estimates of the overall efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From managing stakeholders’ expectations to understanding the functional aspect of the use case to deployment &amp;amp; monitoring of the final solution, you need to manage everything and also need to tackle the day to day challenges your team faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflect&quot;&gt;Reflect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*q9sYzspRddhuguDB&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last phase is to reflect on how the whole project went and what we can take out from it to do better in other upcoming AI projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we need to analyse the results of our deployed solution and compare it with the initially estimated output. We also need to take the customer or business feedback on the results and agree on monitoring and maintenance framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, being an AI project, not everything would go smooth. Every organization has a culture and way of doing things, which may or may not be in line with what we require for our AI initiatives. So based on the lessons learnt from the current AI project, we may need to update our AI strategy &amp;amp; operational framework to suit our opportunities &amp;amp; constraints in a better way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you see, the above approach &amp;amp; framework captures what a business leader or manager needs to know and work out to make AI initiative successful for his organization. It takes vision, strategy, efforts &amp;amp; some self-reflection at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[embed]https://medium.com/\@rathi.ankit/how-to-launch-your-ds-ai-career-in-12-weeks-8a7e6950ffe6[/embed]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ankit Rathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why don’t you connect with Ankit on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rathiankit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/ankitrathi/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is no secret that data is the new oil and AI is the new electricity. Due to the difference AI can make in every walk of life, it is the red hot subject among recent graduates/undergraduates and working professionals in different industries. It is not only up to the technical team to make AI initiatives a success in the organization. Business value creation in driven top-down so business leaders is equally responsible for the success or failure of AI initiatives. If you look at the failure rate of AI projects and the challenges faced by AI teams, you can easily figure out that most of the challenges are because of the absence of data culture in an organization. And data culture can’t be inculcated in a day, it takes efforts and leadership needs to drive it as part of their change management program. Apart from infusing data culture in the organization, most of the decisions in business are made by its leaders, AI is providing huge opportunity to many areas of business across domains. Hence as a leader or manager, understanding AI and applying it effectively in our organization can make all the difference between us and our competitors. Recently I published a book for AI starters and enthusiasts, where I shared a learning framework on how they can get into AI and during my discussions with managers and business leaders, they asked me if a similar framework can be built for business leaders. Framework If we look at the day to day working of managers and leaders, they need not know each and everything of the work &amp;amp; resources they are managing but just enough awareness can make a huge impact on AI initiatives. It helps in setting the right expectations with the customer or business, defining better strategy, anticipating challenges and understanding the concerns of the team. So here is the framework that I came up with for business leaders &amp;amp; managers: Prepare, Strategize, Execute, Reflect. Let us have a look at each of the phase of the above framework: Prepare AI is a new &amp;amp; evolving field, the first phase for us is to prepare ourselves to run these AI initiatives. The very first step we need to take is to navigate the overall landscape. What are AI, ML, DL, DS, DM, BI terms? How they are interconnected? What is the typical lifecycle to execute AI project? What are the different roles and skill-set required in the lifecycle? The second step would be to build the capability to execute AI projects. More we work on our concepts and skill-set, more we will be comfortable to run such projects and handling teams. Strategize After working on our concepts &amp;amp; skill-set, we are ready to work with a team on AI projects but hold on. How do we know what are the opportunities in our organization? Working on which projects would be more beneficial than others? To get answers to these questions, we need to define an AI strategy based on our organization &amp;amp; industry. Apart from defining the strategy, we need to have an operational framework in place to get a clear understanding of what is to be done and who will be doing what. Another area for leaders/manager is to anticipate what challenges their teams would face while working on AI projects. Having a view beforehand will help you to handle the challenges better. Execute This phase covers managing the on-field execution of AI projects. As AI projects are different from typical IT projects, we need to emphasize quick POC to get a better view of the problem &amp;amp; to provide optimized estimates of the overall efforts. From managing stakeholders’ expectations to understanding the functional aspect of the use case to deployment &amp;amp; monitoring of the final solution, you need to manage everything and also need to tackle the day to day challenges your team faces. Reflect The last phase is to reflect on how the whole project went and what we can take out from it to do better in other upcoming AI projects. Firstly, we need to analyse the results of our deployed solution and compare it with the initially estimated output. We also need to take the customer or business feedback on the results and agree on monitoring and maintenance framework. Obviously, being an AI project, not everything would go smooth. Every organization has a culture and way of doing things, which may or may not be in line with what we require for our AI initiatives. So based on the lessons learnt from the current AI project, we may need to update our AI strategy &amp;amp; operational framework to suit our opportunities &amp;amp; constraints in a better way. As you see, the above approach &amp;amp; framework captures what a business leader or manager needs to know and work out to make AI initiative successful for his organization. It takes vision, strategy, efforts &amp;amp; some self-reflection at the end. If you liked the content, check out my post on ‘How to launch your DS/AI Career in 12 weeks?’ [embed]https://medium.com/\@rathi.ankit/how-to-launch-your-ds-ai-career-in-12-weeks-8a7e6950ffe6[/embed] Ankit Rathi is an AI architect, published author &amp;amp; well-known speaker. His interest lies primarily in building end-to-end AI applications/products following best practices of Data Engineering and Architecture. Why don’t you connect with Ankit on Twitter, LinkedIn or Instagram?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Types of Challenges in DS/AI Projects &amp;amp; Initiatives</title><link href="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/08/21/4-types-of-challenges-in-ds-ai-projects-initiatives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Types of Challenges in DS/AI Projects &amp; Initiatives" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/08/21/4-types-of-challenges-in-ds-ai-projects-initiatives</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ankit-rathi.github.io/data-and-ai/markdown/2019/08/21/4-types-of-challenges-in-ds-ai-projects-initiatives.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*jOEJ1xsav6nKYHk-VRD1Xw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by [Eila Lifflander](https://unsplash.com/@3ilaliff?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText) on [Unsplash](https://unsplash.com/search/photos/challenges?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post, I have analyzed frequent challenges encountered by DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts in their projects/initiatives. I have re-organized these challenges into 4 areas of concerns, my idea is to build a framework around these challenges to suggest possible solutions in upcoming posts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS/AI promises considerable economic &amp;amp; social benefits, even as it disrupts the way we work. Almost everyone agrees that it is a field which can change the world, from healthcare to countering terrorism and even arts &amp;amp; sports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts are facing different challenges from ideation to productization, it is estimated that between 70% and 85% of DS/AI projects fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a holistic view of the challenges &amp;amp; failures, I looked at various articles available on the internet about the challenges in DS/AI projects &amp;amp; initiatives. You can find all the articles I referred at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few weeks, I have also spoken to many DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts on this topic and they have also given some useful insights. I will cover these specific insights into the challenges in the upcoming blog-posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to shed some light on the reasons why we observe such a high failure rate, I also analyzed the results of a survey conducted by Kaggle in 2017. You can see the full report &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/surveys/2017&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The part of the survey relevant to this article is about the challenges companies face as far as their DS/AI efforts are concerned. The following chart shows the top fifteen challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*1HEARRre7TJauqQX.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I am still documenting the challenges &amp;amp; possible solutions, I can categorize these challenges in four broad segments: — Cultural challenges (right talent, data literacy, realistic expectations etc) — Data-related challenges (data access, data quality, lifecycle management etc) — Operational challenges (suitable operating model with specific roles &amp;amp; responsibilities) — Technology-related challenges (appropriate tech-stack, right infrastructure etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ai4WsvqwNA8bKjY6BOIBGw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;challenges-in-dsaiprojects&quot;&gt;Challenges in DS/AI Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the above-mentioned sources (surveys, articles &amp;amp; experts) in this post, I have collected all the challenges and tried to categorize them into four areas of concern — Culture, Operation, Data, Technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Quality — Data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talent Gap — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Company Politics — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Access — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Literacy — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Privacy — Data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SME Gap — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heterogeneous Tech-stack — Technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unrealistic Expectations — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Co-ordination with IT &amp;amp; other deptt — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stakeholders’ Buy-in — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sponsorship — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deployment — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Algorithms Limitations — Technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Consolidation — Data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity Assessment — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model Explainability — Technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agility — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Security — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solving the Wrong Problem — Operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organizational Maturity — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Storytelling — Culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;area-of-concerns-indsai&quot;&gt;Area of Concerns in DS/AI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s consolidate the above challenges in the respective area of concerns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cultural-challenges&quot;&gt;Cultural Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Company Politics, Data Literacy, Unrealistic Expectations, Stakeholders’ Buy-in, Organizational Maturity, Storytelling&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;operational-challenges&quot;&gt;Operational Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talent Gap, Data Access, SME Gap, Coordination with IT and other deptts, Deployment, Opportunity Assessment, Data Security, Solving the Wrong Problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;data-challenges&quot;&gt;Data Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Quality, Data Privacy, Data Consolidation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technology-challenges&quot;&gt;Technology Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heterogeneous Tech-stack, Algorithms Limitations, Model Explainability&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that if we categorize these challenges in the respective area of concerns, we can build a framework around it which can address these challenges and suggest possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to explore these possibilities in the upcoming blog-posts, if it looks interesting to you, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you for reading my post. I regularly write about Data &amp;amp; Technology on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/today/posts/ankitrathi?source=post_page---------------------------&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rathi.ankit?source=post_page---------------------------&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;. If you would like to read my future posts then simply ‘Connect’ or ‘Follow’. Also, feel free to visit my webpage&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ankitrathi.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://ankitrathi.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this post, I have analyzed frequent challenges encountered by DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts in their projects/initiatives. I have re-organized these challenges into 4 areas of concerns, my idea is to build a framework around these challenges to suggest possible solutions in upcoming posts. DS/AI promises considerable economic &amp;amp; social benefits, even as it disrupts the way we work. Almost everyone agrees that it is a field which can change the world, from healthcare to countering terrorism and even arts &amp;amp; sports. DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts are facing different challenges from ideation to productization, it is estimated that between 70% and 85% of DS/AI projects fail. To get a holistic view of the challenges &amp;amp; failures, I looked at various articles available on the internet about the challenges in DS/AI projects &amp;amp; initiatives. You can find all the articles I referred at the end of this post. In the past few weeks, I have also spoken to many DS/AI leaders &amp;amp; experts on this topic and they have also given some useful insights. I will cover these specific insights into the challenges in the upcoming blog-posts. In order to shed some light on the reasons why we observe such a high failure rate, I also analyzed the results of a survey conducted by Kaggle in 2017. You can see the full report here. The part of the survey relevant to this article is about the challenges companies face as far as their DS/AI efforts are concerned. The following chart shows the top fifteen challenges: While I am still documenting the challenges &amp;amp; possible solutions, I can categorize these challenges in four broad segments: — Cultural challenges (right talent, data literacy, realistic expectations etc) — Data-related challenges (data access, data quality, lifecycle management etc) — Operational challenges (suitable operating model with specific roles &amp;amp; responsibilities) — Technology-related challenges (appropriate tech-stack, right infrastructure etc). Challenges in DS/AI Projects Based on the above-mentioned sources (surveys, articles &amp;amp; experts) in this post, I have collected all the challenges and tried to categorize them into four areas of concern — Culture, Operation, Data, Technology: Data Quality — Data Talent Gap — Operations Company Politics — Culture Data Access — Operations Data Literacy — Culture Data Privacy — Data SME Gap — Operations Heterogeneous Tech-stack — Technology Unrealistic Expectations — Culture Co-ordination with IT &amp;amp; other deptt — Operations Stakeholders’ Buy-in — Culture Sponsorship — Culture Deployment — Operations Algorithms Limitations — Technology Data Consolidation — Data Opportunity Assessment — Operations Model Explainability — Technology Agility — Operations Data Security — Operations Solving the Wrong Problem — Operations Organizational Maturity — Culture Storytelling — Culture Area of Concerns in DS/AI Now, let’s consolidate the above challenges in the respective area of concerns: Cultural Challenges Company Politics, Data Literacy, Unrealistic Expectations, Stakeholders’ Buy-in, Organizational Maturity, Storytelling Operational Challenges Talent Gap, Data Access, SME Gap, Coordination with IT and other deptts, Deployment, Opportunity Assessment, Data Security, Solving the Wrong Problem Data Challenges Data Quality, Data Privacy, Data Consolidation Technology Challenges Heterogeneous Tech-stack, Algorithms Limitations, Model Explainability What next? I believe that if we categorize these challenges in the respective area of concerns, we can build a framework around it which can address these challenges and suggest possible solutions. I intend to explore these possibilities in the upcoming blog-posts, if it looks interesting to you, stay tuned. Thank you for reading my post. I regularly write about Data &amp;amp; Technology on LinkedIn &amp;amp; Medium. If you would like to read my future posts then simply ‘Connect’ or ‘Follow’. Also, feel free to visit my webpage https://ankitrathi.com</summary></entry></feed>